[music]
[संगीत]
Welcome Vijendra Sir. The entry is good
विजेंद्र सर का स्वागत है। एंट्री अच्छी
But the sitting style is still very casual
है लेकिन बैठने का तरीका अभी बड़ा कैजुअल
Is.
है।
Now you can discover a hidden side of yourself through this podcast
इस पॉडकास्ट के थ्रू आपकी एक हिडन साइड अब
People will see it. This is very interesting
लोगों को दिखेगी। ये बहुत इंटरेस्टिंग
It is the beginning. you are known for taking interview
आरंभ है। यू आर नोन फॉर टेकिंग इंटरव्यू
Sir. But you guys need to be a little psychologically
सर। बट आप लोगों को साइकोलॉजिकली थोड़ा सा
You can scan it. there is no milkman
स्कैन कर लेते हो। दूध का दू्हा कोई नहीं
Would. We all have biases and you
होता। हम सबके अंदर बायसेस होते और आप
but still I won't judge him
कहेगा लेकिन फिर भी मैं इसे जज नहीं
I will do it. Ultimately your character
करूंगा। अल्टीमेटली आपके कैरेक्टर का
The test is the same.
टेस्ट वही है।
would you say that confidence is the most
वुड यू से दैट कॉन्फिडेंस इज द मोस्ट
Important thing in any job profile?
इंपोर्टेंट थिंग इन एनी जॉब प्रोफाइल?
If I talk in my language, I would say
मेरी वाली भाषा में बात करें तो मैं कहता
If you don't have it you can't get five
हूं अगर आपके पास यह नहीं है कि आप पांच
If you can tolerate failure then do it straight away
फेलियर बर्दाश्त कर सकते हैं तो सीधा
Don't think of becoming an IAS then. A Reality
आईएएस बनने की मत सोचो फिर। एक रियलिटी
Check it.
चेक कीजिए।
What is the point of this whole 22 year old person?
22 साल का इंसान इस पूरे पॉइंट से क्या
He will gain it. For a 22 year old kid I
गेन कर लेगा। 22 साल के बच्चे के लिए मैं
I say this to those who are trying to succeed fast
यह कहता हूं जो तेजी से सफल होने की
There is aspiration. There might be something besides this too.
आकांक्षा है। इसके अलावा भी कुछ होगी ना।
Hitler had everything. Hitler's
हिटलर के पास तो सब कुछ था। हिटलर की
Was life a purposeful life? So
जिंदगी पर्पसफुल जिंदगी थी क्या? सो
The only sure thing is what the ultimate purpose is
अल्टीमेट पर्पस जो है वो केवल यह श्योर
Shot quick success cannot be considered.
शॉट क्विक सक्सेस को नहीं माना जा सकता।
We need to go beyond that.
वी नीड टू गो बियोंड दैट।
Judge of humans in the social media generation
सोशल मीडिया की जनरेशन में इंसानों की जज
The capacity to do this has increased a lot. Brother
करने की कैपेसिटी ज्यादा बढ़ चुकी है। भई
You are sitting happily. Now a great car
आप मस्त बैठे हुए हैं। अब एक शानदार कार
I am going in. and then you pass a judgement
में जा रहे हैं। और फिर आप एक जजमेंट पास
We do. Poor people do not work hard.
करते हैं। गरीब लोग मेहनत करते ही नहीं।
Where is it coming from? it is coming from
कहां से आ रहा है? इट इज कमिंग फ्रॉम
Pure. Because a lot of things are situational
प्योर। क्योंकि बहुत सारी चीजें सिचुएशनल
also happens. If you are from Uttar Pradesh,
भी होती है। अगर आप उत्तर प्रदेश के,
There are boys from Bihar and Rajasthan. If
बिहार के, राजस्थान के लड़के हैं। अगर
Did you think of becoming an IAS?
आपके मन में आईएएस बनने के बारे में आया
If it is, then it should be rejected. But
है तो उसको खारिज कर देना चाहिए। लेकिन
If you are a girl from this area.
अगर आप इस इलाके से आई हुई लड़की हैं।
You are offered a home visit that
आपको घर से यह प्रस्ताव दिया जाता है कि
Son, go to Delhi and get ready. quick pounce
बेटा दिल्ली जाओ तैयारी कर लो। झट से झपट
Let's take
के ले
Take it. Our country was such a society for a long time
लीजिए। हमारा ही देश एक समय तक ऐसा समाज
in whose rules it was stated that the person who
था जिसके नियमों में था कि वह व्यक्ति जो
He will be expelled from the community across the ocean
समंदर पार जाएगा उसे बिरादरी से निकाल
should be given. What did he want? He probably is this
दिया जाए। वो क्या चाहता था? वो शायद यह
I wanted your eyes not to open.
चाहता था कि आपकी आंखें ना खुले।
A simple life is just a geometry notebook
सरल जिंदगी तो केवल ज्योमेट्री की नोटबुक
in which a scale was placed and
में दिखाई थी जिसमें एक स्केल रखा और
Drawn with pencil. life in a straight line
पेंसिल से खींची। जिंदगियां सरल रेखा में
moving
चलती
[music]
[संगीत]
Was. Friends, there are so many of Vijendra Sir's
थी। दोस्तों, विजेंद्र सर के इतने सारे
UPSC videos have gone viral
वीडियोस वायरल हुए हैं यूपीएससी
In the students' circuit. But my promise
स्टूडेंट्स के सर्किट में। बट मेरा वादा
I want you to know about an unknown side of these people today.
आपसे यह है कि आज आप इनकी एक अननोन साइड
You will see it in this episode. but my intention is this
देखोगे इस एपिसोड पे। बट मेरी इंटेंशन यह
also that whoever watches this episode
भी है कि जो भी इंसान यह वाला एपिसोड देखे
Any young Indian who watches this episode
जो भी यंग भारतीय यह वाला एपिसोड देखे
He got value from this episode. This
उन्हें वैल्यू मिले इस एपिसोड से। इस
The theme of the episode is maturity. and this
एपिसोड की थीम है मैच्योरिटी। और यह
The episode also gives you a notebook and pen
एपिसोड भी आपको एक नोटबुक और पेन साथ में
Will have to keep it and consume it. Because we have a
रखकर कंज्यूम करना होगा। क्योंकि हमने एक
Introducing the algorithm of maturity to you
मैच्योरिटी का एल्गोरिदम पेश किया आपके
Through this whole episode in front of us. told you
सामने इस पूरे एपिसोड के थ्रू। आपको बताया
That you can achieve more maturity in your own life
कि आप खुद की लाइफ में ज्यादा मैच्योरिटी
How can you attract? more yourself
कैसे अट्रैक्ट कर सकते हो। खुद ज्यादा
How can you become mature and take care of your life
मैच्योर कैसे बन सकते हो और खुद की लाइफ
both the quality and success potential of
की क्वालिटी और सक्सेस पोटेंशियल दोनों को
How can you provide benefits? of one's own mind
फायदे कैसे दे सकते हो? खुद के दिमाग के
Come inside. Go inside your own heart and
अंदर घुसो। खुद के दिल के अंदर घुसो और
Change your own mind set. This Special
खुद के माइंड सेट को बदलो। इस स्पेशल
Episodes through Vijendra Sir and Ranveer's
एपिसोड के थ्रू विजेंद्र सर और रणवीर के
with TRS
साथ टीआरएस पर
[music]
[संगीत]
Welcome Vijendra Sir to The Ranveer Show.
विजेंद्र सर का स्वागत है द रणवीर शो में।
Thanks Ranveer. I know that this
शुक्रिया रणवीर। मैं जानता हूं कि इस
A lot of people get to know through podcasts
पडकास्ट के थ्रू ना लोगों को बहुत सारी
A chance to learn practical things
प्रैक्टिकल चीजों को सीखने का एक चांस
will get. but at the same time too much
मिलेगा। बट एट द सेम टाइम बहुत ज्यादा
You will find peace from this conversation. so thank you
सुकून मिलेगा इस कन्वर्सेशन से। सो थैंक
You for being in the studio. It is very
यू फॉर बीइंग इन द स्टूडियो। यह बहुत
interesting start because usually
इंटरेस्टिंग आरंभ है क्योंकि आमतौर पर
I've been told ah the exact opposite.
मुझे अह इसके ठीक विपरीत कहा जाता रहा है।
Ah, even if it's the interview world
अह चाहे वो इंटरव्यू वाली दुनिया हो उसमें
It is said that sitting in front of you Sir, one
कहा जाता है कि सर आपके सामने बैठने से एक
So, they become restless. Secondly I also constantly
तो बेचैन होते हैं। दूसरा मुझे भी लगातार
It seems to make people a bit restless
ये लगता रहा है कि लोगों को थोड़ा बेचैन
It is more important to get it done. so for a
किया जाना ज्यादा जरूरी है। इसलिए फॉर अ
change you are telling me this about me
चेंज आप मुझे मेरे बारे में ये कह रहे हैं
that I will give you peace. So thank you. thank you
कि मुझसे सुकून मिलेगा। सो थैंक यू। थैंक
You for saying it. yes, you have a hidden side
यू फॉर सेइंग इट। हां, आपकी एक हिडन साइड
Now people will see it. How are you all? uh i
अब लोगों को दिखेगी। कैसे हो सब? अह मैं
I am fine. I'm learning things and
अच्छा हूं। चीजें सीख रहा हूं और जैसा
You said that in conversations with you outside, there were many
आपने कहा कि बाहर आपसे बातचीत में बहुत
all the things that you normally do when you
सारी ऐसी चीजें जो कि आमतौर पे आप जब आप
When you turn 50, your ego starts to take over you.
50 साल के होते हैं तो आपकी एक ईगो आपको
She is stopping that from a 32 year old person
रोक रही होती है कि 32 साल के व्यक्ति से
There is nothing to learn. but i learned a lot
कुछ सीखना नहीं है। लेकिन आई लर्न अ लॉट
In this conversation. so yes i am looking
इन दिस कन्वर्सेशन। सो यस आई एम लुकिंग
Forward to the hole. now it's my turn to
फॉरवर्ड टू द होल। नाउ इट्स माय टर्न टू
Learn. yes yes yes
लर्न। जी जी जी
Let's start with practicality. Wood You
शुरुआत करते हैं प्रैक्टिकिटी से। वुड यू
say that confidence is the most important thing in
से दैट कॉन्फिडेंस इज द मोस्टेंट थिंग इन
Any industry in any job profile and is
एनी इंडस्ट्री इन एनी जॉब प्रोफाइल और इज
it's other aspects and this is why I tell you
इट अदर एस्पेक्ट्स और यह मैं आपसे इसलिए
I am asking because obviously a
पूछ रहा हूं क्योंकि ऑब्वियसली अ
you are known for taking interview sir but in
यू आर नोन फॉर टेकिंग इंटरव्यू सर बट इन
My eyes are a little psychologically sensitive to you guys
माय आईज आप लोगों को साइकोलॉजिकली थोड़ा
you just scan it and that is the actual
सा स्कैन कर लेते हो एंड दैट इज द एक्चुअल
Craft That You're Getting Better at Even
क्राफ्ट दैट यू आर गेटिंग बेटर एट इवन
Today I am right to set, which means I am trying
टुडे एम आई राइट टू सेट मतलब मैं कोशिश कर
I have been and it is true that when you, for example,
रहा हूं और ये बात सच है कि जब आप मसलन
I'm talking to you right now or just a little bit
मैं इस समय आपसे बात कर रहा हूं या थोड़ी
I was talking to you a while ago, I
देर पहले मैं आपसे बात कर रहा था तो मैं
When I meet a person who
जब किसी व्यक्ति से मिलता हूं जिसमें
If interviews are involved then I would like to introduce the person to
इंटरव्यूज शामिल है तो मैं व्यक्ति को
I read it almost like I read a book
लगभग लगभग वैसे पढ़ता हूं जैसे किताब पढ़ी
She goes. There are mistakes in reading this book too
जाती है। ये किताब पढ़ने में भी गलतियां
May be possible. So there is no such claim
हो सकती हैं। इसलिए ऐसा कोई दावा नहीं है
That whatever I read is exactly like that.
कि जिसे मैंने जैसा पढ़ा वो ठीक वैसा है।
But it is definitely, as you said, a
लेकिन यह जरूर है कि जैसा आपने कहा एक
Craft is a skill. There is a skill that
क्राफ्ट एक स्किल है। एक कौशल है जिसमें
When you meet people regularly, you
आप लगातार जब लोगों से मिलते हैं तब आप
could see the ratio of that personality of his
उनके उस व्यक्तित्व के रेश्यो को देख पाते
Are. As far as we are concerned this is a matter of confidence
हैं। हम जहां तक ये आत्मविश्वास वाली बात
It depends on where you look
आपने कही देखिए ये इस बात पर निर्भर करेगा
What do you call confidence? What
कि आप आत्मविश्वास कहते किसे हैं? क्या
Confidence simply means that who
आत्मविश्वास का मतलब सिर्फ इतना है कि कौन
Can speak the loudest. Who is the most
सबसे ज्यादा तेज बोल सकता है। कौन सबसे
Can scream louder or show more confidence
ज्यादा तेज चीख सकता है या आत्मविश्वास का
It just means that I have it inside me
मतलब सिर्फ इतना है कि मैं मेरे अंदर यह
I feel proud that I am the only one who is right. then no
दंभ हो कि मैं ही केवल ठीक हूं। तो नहीं
Such confidence which neither leads to success nor
ऐसा आत्मविश्वास जो है वह ना तो सफलता ना
Neither job nor life is the best thing for them
नौकरी ना जिंदगी उनके लिए सबसे अच्छी चीज
Not there. Is it okay? When we are confident
नहीं है। ठीक है ना? जब हम आत्मविश्वास का
to understand it in a slightly nuanced manner
को थोड़ा सा न्यूस्ड रूप में समझने की
Let's try. when it simply means that
कोशिश करते हैं। जब जिसका सीधा मतलब यह है
That you don't look down on yourself.
कि आप खुद को लुक डाउन नहीं करते हैं।
feeling completely sorry for oneself or
अपने आप को एकदम बेचारगी से भरा हुआ या
Don't be filled with self-pity. If
आत्मदया से भरा हुआ नहीं रखते हैं। यदि
Confidence means that definitely
आत्मविश्वास का मतलब वह है तो डेफिनेटली
Confidence helps, it helps.
आत्मविश्वास हेल्प करता है, मदद करता है।
But the world will be more beautiful. If we take this
लेकिन दुनिया और खूबसूरत होगी। अगर हम इस
from binary viewpoints of sorts
तरह के बाइनरी में बटे हुए दृष्टिकोणों से
Don't look. Do not look at it like that, there are some people who
ना देखें। ऐसे ना देखें कि कुछ लोग हैं जो
are full of confidence and some people
आत्मविश्वास से भरे हुए हैं और कुछ लोग
who are filled with helplessness. Because
हैं जो बेचारगी से भरे हुए हैं। क्योंकि
Many things are also situational. What
बहुत सारी चीजें सिचुएशनल भी होती है। किस
How do you behave in the situation?
परिस्थिति में आप कैसा बिहेव करते हैं।
That is ultimately the test of your character
अल्टीमेटली आपके कैरेक्टर का टेस्ट वही
Is. We are wow. Ok. Firstly I would say that
है। हम वाओ। ओके। पहले तो मैं ये कहना
I would like that social media
चाहूंगा कि सोशल मीडिया की
This generation has come to think of judging people
जनरेशन में आई थिंक इंसानों की जज करने की
The capacity has increased a lot. yes it is
कैपेसिटी ज्यादा बढ़ चुकी है। यस इट्स
Being rewarded unfortunately. Judging Others
बीइंग रिवॉर्डेड अनफॉर्चुनेटली। जजिंग अदर
Human beings are being rewarded. yes,
ह्यूमन बीइंग्स इज़ बीइंग रिवार्डेड। यस,
That's what the sad part is. it is
दैट्स दैट्स व्हाट द सेड पार्ट इज। इट इज
Making everybody more judgemental. in the 90s it
मेकिंग एवरीबडी मोर जजमेंटल। 90ज में यह
It wasn’t true, was it? Less to Less Extent It
सच नहीं था ना? लेस टू लेसर एक्सटेंट इट
Habitat. Not to this extent. Ok. and you
वास। नॉट टू दिस एक्सटेंट। ओके। एंड यू
See the increase of judgement. Hazli Hazli It
सीन द इनक्रीस ऑफ़ जजमेंट। हजली हजली इट
There is enough social media and there is one reason for this
हैज़ इनफ सोशल मीडिया इज वन रीज़ जिसकी वजह
It has increased since. But as I said in society
से यह बढ़ा है। बट एज आई सेड सोसाइटी में
The thing that will be rewarded by the society
जिस चीज को रिवॉर्ड किया जाएगा सोसाइटी का
it will become the nature of the thing to
की प्रकृति हो जाएगी कि वह उस चीज को और
Will start imbibing more. him more
ज्यादा इंबाइप करने लगेगा। उसको ज्यादा
To see. In our time, I had this problem even till 90's
देखने। हमारे समय में मुझे 90ज तक भी यह
I know that hate was something that could be
पता है कि नफरत एक ऐसी चीज थी जिसे जिसे
Incentivisation was not given. who has bad
इंसेंटिवाइज नहीं किया जाता था। जिसे बुरी
It was seen with eyes. Is it okay? So they
नजर से देखा जाता था। ठीक है ना? इसलिए वे
Even the people who had hatred inside them, their
लोग भी जिनके अंदर नफरत थी, उनकी यह
I was forced to hide that hatred a little bit
मजबूरी थी कि उस नफरत को थोड़ा सा छिपा ले
let's go. It felt the same way about many other things
जाए। ऐसा ही बाकी बहुत सारी चीजों पे लगा
come into force. Being judgemental is part of that
लागू होता है। जजमेंटल होना उसी में से
It comes out. when you look at things people
निकल कर आता है। जब आप चीज लोगों को देखते
It is not just for the people. my worry is
हैं लोगों को ही नहीं। मेरी तो चिंता
More than people. communities, groups
लोगों से ज्यादा है। समुदायों को, समूहों
to groups, identities, nationalities
को, ग्रुप्स को, आइडेंटिटीज को, नेशनलिटीज
To. When you see these people and say
को। आप जब इन लोगों को देखते हैं और कहते
It is not so, this is what it takes to be judgemental,
हैं नहीं ये तो ये जो जजमेंटल होना है,
Where does it ultimately come from? just think about it
अल्टीमेटली आता कहां से है? जरा सोच के
Look at this. Think on the level of psychology
देखिए ना। मनोविज्ञान के स्तर पे सोचेंगे
But it will come out clear. being judgemental comes
बट क्लियर निकल कर आएगा। जजमेंटल होना आता
It is because of our intellectual laziness. it is always
है हमारे बौद्धिक आलस्य से। इट इज ऑलवेज
Intellectual laziness means that our
बौद्धिक आलस्य का मतलब है कि हमारे हम जो
Humans want to do intellectual rigging
इंटेलेक्चुअल रिगर करना चाहते हैं इंसान
He is a bit lazy by nature.
अपनी प्रकृति में थोड़ा सा आलसी होता है।
If he finds a way in which
अगर उसे ऐसा कोई रास्ता मिलता है जिसमें
that it will take a little less effort and you will have no time to go there
कि थोड़े कम मेहनत लगेगी और वहीं जाने का
There is another way in which a little
दूसरा रास्ता मिलता है जिसमें थोड़ी
If it takes more hard work then most of the time it
ज्यादा मेहनत लगेगी तो मोस्ट ऑफ द टाइम वो
Chooses the path that requires less effort. this man
कम मेहनत वाला रास्ता चुनता है। ये मनुष्य
It is in the nature to conserve energy. it
की प्रकृति में है टू कंजर्व एनर्जी। यह
It happens at the mental level as well. when we
मेंटल लेवल पर भी होता है। जब हम
Let's look at the stereotypes when we give
स्टीरियोटाइप्स को देखते हैं, जब हम दिए
Let us look at the decisions that have been made, which are based on decisions already made
गए फैसलों को देखते हैं, जो पहले से फैसले
have been given and we say this way
दे दिए गए हैं और हम कहते हैं इस रास्ते
If we walk with this we don't have to work hard
से चलेंगे तो हमें कोई मेहनत नहीं करनी
Will need it. This person is coming. its beard
पड़ेगी। ये व्यक्ति आ रहा है। इसकी दाढ़ी
is it visible or its turban is visible
दिखाई दे रही है या इसकी पगड़ी दिखाई दे
It has been happening. It means this is what it means.
रही है। इसका मतलब ये ऐसा होता है।
Because their community is like this. How much
क्योंकि इनका समुदाय ऐसा होता है। कितना
It became easy, right? Life is sorted. To you
आसान हो गया ना? लाइफ इज सॉर्टेड। आपको
Judges Judgments have been served and you only
सर्व कर दिए गए जज जजमेंट्स और आपको केवल
They have to be implemented. on people like this
उनको लागू करना है। इस तरह के लोगों पर यह
This intellectual laziness is what affects such people.
इस तरह के लोगों पर यह जो बौद्धिक आलस्य
it's worth it to be judgemental because it
है इसकी कीमत है जजमेंटल होना क्योंकि यह
It's just like pronunciation in a language
ठीक वैसे है जैसे भाषा में प्रोनाउंस
Pronouns are used more
प्रोनाउंस का इस्तेमाल ज्यादा होता है
The value of noun is less because for noun
नाउन का कम होता है क्योंकि नाउन के लिए
you should know okay you should know
आपको पता होना चाहिए ठीक है ना आपको पता
This should be Ranveer and in his place
होना चाहिए ये रणवीर है और इसकी जगह पे
Say he is a human being, now if he is a human being then it will be easy
कहें ये इंसान है अब इंसान है तो आसान हो
I went and showed my two hands, two legs and two eyes
गया दो हाथ दो पांव दो आंख दिखा दिया
the person is gone the matter is over so the pronunciation which
इंसान हो गया बात खत्म सो प्रोनाउंस जो
are pronouns are always easier
हैं सर्वनाम जो है वो हमेशा आसान होते हैं
So it is always easy to be judgemental
इसलिए जजमेंटल होना हमेशा आसान होता है हम
We are judgemental because we suffer from intellectual laziness.
जजमेंटल हैं क्योंकि हम बौद्धिक आलस्य के
Reasons to avoid doing intellectual work
कारण बौद्धिक श्रम करने से बचना चाहते हैं
Basically if we are more involved in your life
हम बेसिकली अगर आपकी जिंदगी में ज्यादा
You have free time, you are more judgemental
फ्री टाइम है, आप ज्यादा जजमेंटल हो
You will go. Not one, that is also one thing.
जाओगे। नाट्स वन दैट इज आल्सो वन थिंग।
That's why it is very important to stay busy
इसलिए बिजी रहना बहुत जरूरी है क्योंकि
If you become too judgemental
अगर आप ज्यादा जजमेंटल हो गए
There is no self harm factor here
यहां ना एक सेल्फ हार्म का फैक्टर भी
The form is formed because you judge yourself as well
फॉर्म हो जाता है क्योंकि आप खुद को भी जज
You start doing it. Ok. In fact, I alone
करने लगते हो। ओके। दरअसल मैंने जो अकेली
I have learnt something but I have not learnt to judge. Anj
चीज सीखी है वो जज करना नहीं सीखी। अनज
Learn to do and learn to un-judge
करना सीखिए और अनज करना जज करने से जाहिर
that is more difficult because you
है कि ज्यादा मुश्किल होता है क्योंकि आप
Know your bias. You need your
अपने बायसिस को जानते हैं। आपको अपने
Biases are knowing your prejudices. His
बायसेस अपने पूर्वग्रह पता हैं। उसके
Despite this, there is no one who is one's own groom.
बावजूद और खुद का दूल्हा कोई नहीं होता।
We all have biases. Is it okay?
हम सबके अंदर बायसेस होते हैं। ठीक है ना?
There will definitely be prejudices. This which
पूर्वग्रह होंगे ही होंगे। यह जो
You have prejudices even when you know them
पूर्वाग्रह हैं आप इनको जानते हुए भी जब
those prejudices in front of you
आपके सामने उन पूर्वाग्रहों से ग्रस्त
Someone who is supposed to be there comes and you say that
होने वाला कोई व्यक्ति आया और आप कहें कि
I know I have this prejudice
मैं जानता हूं कि मेरे अंदर यह पूर्वग्रह
But still, I won't judge it.
है लेकिन फिर भी मैं इसे जज नहीं करूंगा।
it takes a lot of debt and also a lot
इट टेक्स लॉट ऑफ करज एंड आल्सो एक बहुत
As said in all this, a lot of intellectual labour is involved.
सारी इसमें बहुत जैसा कहा बौद्धिक श्रम की
There is a need also. Being Judgmental Is In
जरूरत भी पड़ती है। बीइंग जजमेंटल इज इन
Due course by default. Being Unjustified
ड्यू कोर्स बाय डिफॉल्ट। बीइंग अनजमेंटल
is always conscious.
इज ऑलवेज कॉन्शियस।
There is more to talk about.
इसके बारे में ज्यादा बात करनी है।
Consciously Undoing the Judgment in Your Own
कॉन्शियसली अनडूइंग द जजमेंट इन योर ओन
Mind. But before we talk about it
माइंड। पर इसके बारे में बात करने से पहले
It is a very simple question sir. Somebody 22 years old
बहुत सरल सा सवाल है सर। कोई 22 साल का
What will a person gain from this whole point?
इंसान इस पूरे पॉइंट से क्या गेन कर लेगा?
For one's own practical life, for one's own
खुद के प्रैक्टिकल लाइफ के लिए, खुद के
For career. Look, what happens is that
करियर के लिए। देखिए, होता क्या है कि
Where do our voices come from? Our
हमारे वॉइससेस कहां से आते हैं? हमारे
Just like we said that through that socialization
वसेस जैसे हमने कहा कि उस सोशलाइजेशन से
We will come and we will come from our comfort zone. You
आएंगे और हमारे कंफर्ट ज़ोन से आएंगे। आप
Are you able to understand? This is a comfort zone. You
समझ पा रहे हैं? यह एक कंफर्ट जोन है। आप
Born as a man. you are a bengali
पुरुष की तरह पैदा हुए। आप एक बंगाली की
Like, you were born a Punjabi. Correct
तरह, आप एक पंजाबी की तरह पैदा हुए। ठीक
Isn't it? In what particular way were you born
है ना? आप किस पर्टिकुलर तरीके से आप पैदा
happened? Because of that you have a comfort zone
हुए? उसके कारण आपका एक कंफर्ट ज़ोन बन गया
Is. and you want to be in that comfort zone
है। एंड यू वांट टू बी इन दैट कंफर्ट ज़ोन
Because as I said that we all are from nature
बिकॉज़ एज आई सेड कि हम सब लोग प्रकृति से
They are lazy. So out of the comfort zone
आलसी होते हैं। इसलिए कंफर्ट ज़ोन से बाहर
It will take effort to get out. go to a place like this
निकलने में मेहनत लगेगी। ऐसी जगह पे जाना
Which will be a place of discomfort. Example
पड़ेगा जो डिसकंफर्ट वाली जगह होगी। उदाहरण
Let us understand from this. Suppose any IIT
से समझते हैं। मान लीजिए कोई आईआईटी
Bombay is a nice place. Top IIT is the country
बॉम्बे अच्छी जगह है। टॉप आईआईटी है देश
Of. People from all over the country come to IIT Bombay
का। पूरे देश के लोग आईआईटी बॉम्बे आने की
Let's try. Let's assume Actius
कोशिश करते हैं। मान लेते हैं एक्टिशियस
let's assume in the sense that let's assume
सेंस में मान लेते हैं कि मान लेते हैं
Is there any child from Azamgarh? he worked hard
आजमगढ़ का कोई बच्चा है। उसने मेहनत की
I cracked IIT JEE and Advanced
एकदम आईआईटी जेई क्रैक किया, एडवांस क्रैक
He did it and reached IIT Bombay.
किया और वो आईआईटी बॉम्बे पहुंच गया।
In that, let's assume it to be mechanical
उसमें मान लेते हैं उसको मैकेनिकल
I got engineering. Now just think about it
इंजीनियरिंग मिल गया। अब जरा सोच के देखिए
He comes here and says that he is from Azamgarh
यहां आए और वो ये कहे कि मुझे आजमगढ़ के
I want children. Was in Azamgarh. from Azamgarh
बच्चे चाहिए। आजमगढ़ में था। आजमगढ़ के
He knows the language of children. their same
बच्चों वाली भाषा उसको आती है। उनका वही
He has that mindset. Everything is there.
वाला माइंडसेट उसको आता है। सब कुछ है।
What is his comfort zone? from Azamgarh
उसका कंफर्ट जोन क्या है? आजमगढ़ के
Children. Even if he comes to IIT Bombay
बच्चे। अगर वो आईआईटी बॉम्बे आकर भी
Because he tells other people a particular
क्योंकि वो बाकी लोगों को एक पर्टिकुलर
judges in a manner. So, choose according to your comfort
तरीके से जज करता है। इसलिए अपने कंफर्ट
Tries to stay in the zone. Will He
जोन में ही रहने की कोशिश करता है। विल ही
Ever be able to actually learn? No. I am 20
एवर बी एबल टू एक्चुअली लर्न? नो। मैं 20
I am telling this for a 22 year old kid. 202
22 साल के बच्चे के लिए बता रहा हूं। 202
year old children when out of this judgemental
साल के बच्चे जब इस इस जजमेंटल से बाहर
When this child from Azamgarh comes here
आते हैं आजमगढ़ का यह बच्चा जब यहां के
To the people of Mumbai, to the people of Gujarat
मुंबई के लोगों को गुजरात के लोगों को
The people of Kashmir live with them instead
कश्मीर के लोगों को इनके साथ रहता है बजाय
If you search for the children of Azamgarh then
आजमगढ़ के बच्चों को ढूंढ के रहने के तो
He is challenging himself. Your bias
वो अपने को चैलेंज कर रहा है। अपने बायसिस
is challenging the . to your presages
को चैलेंज कर रहा है। अपने प्रेजसेस को
He is challenging. to be judgemental of yourself
चैलेंज कर रहा है। अपने जजमेंटल होने को
He is challenging. and she gives him her in return
चैलेंज कर रहा है। और उसे उसे बदले में
what are you getting? give him a
क्या मिल रहा है? उसे बदले में एक
Diversity is being achieved. this diversity
डायवर्सिटी मिल रही है। यह डायवर्सिटी
Hazily Contributes to Her Personality
उसकी पर्सनालिटी को हजली कंट्रीब्यूट
will do it. In Other Words Judgment 22 years old
करेगी। इन अदर वर्ड्स जजमेंट 22 साल के
I am saying this for the child. Right now I am very
बच्चे के लिए कह रहा हूं। अभी मैं बहुत
I am not giving any deep thoughts. 22 year olds
डीप थॉट नहीं दे रहा हूं। 22 साल के बच्चे
for or 20 years old child non
के लिए या 20 साल के बच्चे के लिए नॉन
Being judgemental is fighting that battle with yourself
जजमेंटल होना अपने आप से वह लड़ाई लड़ना
in which he is out of his comfort zone
है जिसमें कि वह अपने कंफर्ट जोन से बाहर
He learns to come. Because being judgemental
आना सीखता है। क्योंकि जजमेंटल होना
Have to be in the comfort zone. not be judgemental
कंफर्ट ज़ोन में होना है। जजमेंटल ना होना
The comfort zone has to be breached. going out
कंफर्ट ज़ोन को ब्रीच करना है। बाहर जाना
Is. I have to go to a place where you feel uncomfortable. Then
है। डिसकंफर्ट वाली जगह पे जाना है। फिर
I have done a Geography but this matter
मैंने एक ज्योग्राफी का लेकिन ये मामला
It does not apply only to geography. If
सिर्फ ज्योग्राफी पे लागू नहीं होता। अगर
You are comfortable only with boys.
आप केवल लड़कों में कंफर्टेबल होते हैं।
But there are girls in your group,
लेकिन आपके ग्रुप के अंदर लड़कियां हैं,
Are speakers of another language. Second
दूसरी भाषा बोलने वाले हैं। दूसरी
There are people with different sexual preferences. Second
सेक्सुअल प्रेफरेंसेस के लोग हैं। दूसरी
They are people of nationality. people of other religions
नेशनलिटी के लोग हैं। दूसरे धर्म के लोग
Are. There are people of other castes. So what?
हैं। दूसरी जाति के लोग हैं। तो क्या हुआ?
You have a diverse peer group. every
आपके पास एक डायवर्स पीियर ग्रुप बना। हर
Interacting with one will be teaching you.
एक से इंटरेक्ट करना आपको सिखा रहा होगा।
Just like if you have a thousand podcasts
ठीक वैसे जैसे आप अगर हजार पॉडकास्ट आपने
For all these years, everyone has given you something
लिए पिछले इतने सालों में हर एक आपको कुछ
He taught me because he was different from you.
सिखा के गया क्योंकि वो आपसे भिन्न था।
It was different from you. If you say no I
आपसे भिन्न था। अगर आप कहे नहीं मैं तो
I am Ranveer and I am Ranveer's podcast
रणवीर हूं और मैं रणवीर का ही पॉडकास्ट
I will do it.
करूंगा।
You having only people like you agreeing
यू हैविंग ओनली पर्सन्स लाइक यू एग्रीइंग
on everything with you will you be able to
ऑन एवरीथिंग विद यू विल यू बी एबल टू
Learn? No you will be able to learn a little.
लर्न? नो यू विल बी एबल टू लर्न अ लिटिल।
This is what I called Disarrayments Lead
दिस इज व्हाट आई कॉल्ड डिसए्रीमेंट्स लीड
To the depths. Yes. Essentially Not Just
टू डेप्थ। यस। एसेंशियली नॉट जस्ट
Disagreement. Every situation is different from your own,
डिसएग्रीमेंट। अपने से भिन्न हर स्थिति,
Every situation that is different from your comfort zone
अपने कंफर्ट जोन से भिन्न हर एक स्थिति
Teaches you. makes you a better person
आपको सिखाती है। आपको बेहतर इंसान बनाती
Is. And the most important thing is that it's inside you
है। और सबसे महत्वपूर्ण बात आपके अंदर वो
It brings maturity. the maturity you
मैच्योरिटी लाती है। जो मैच्योरिटी आपको
It teaches that a person should
ये सिखाती है कि किसी व्यक्ति को किसी
Don't judge a book by its cover.
किताब को उसके कवर देखकर जज मत कीजिए।
Don't judge a person by his appearance
किसी इंसान को उसकी अपीयरेंस देखकर जज मत
Do it. on the basis of his language, his religion,
कीजिए। उसकी भाषा के आधार पर, उसकी धर्म,
his caste or any of his identity
उसकी जाति या उसकी कोई भी आइडेंटिटी के
Don't judge on that basis. Where will this come from? it
आधार पर जज मत कीजिए। ये कहां से आएगा? यह
it will come when you are ready for it
आएगा जब आप इस बात के लिए तैयार होंगे
from the inside that you are out of your comfort zone
अंदर से कि आप अपने कंफर्ट जोन से बाहर
The easiest intellectual ever to come
आएंगे जो अब तक का सबसे आसान बौद्धिक
Laziness' way was to judge someone
आलस्य का तरीका था कि जज जज कर जाइए किसी
If it is a boy then it will be like this, if it is a girl then it will be like this
को लड़का है तो ऐसा होगा लड़की है तो ऐसी
If it comes from LGBTQ then it will be like this
होगी एलजीबीटी क्यू से आता है तो ऐसा होगा
etc etc what does this mean for you
वगैरह वगैरह इसका मतलब क्या है अपने
Coming out of the comfort zone that's the key thing
कंफर्ट ज़ोन से बाहर आना दैट इज दी की थिंग
And you should not be unjudgmental or judgmental.
और आपको अनजमेंटल होना या जजमेंटल ना होना
Actually this is what it teaches, keep in mind this is easy
दरअसल यही सिखाता है ध्यान रखिएगा यह आसान
is not the way because you constantly have to
रास्ता नहीं है क्योंकि आपको लगातार अपने
We have to fight prejudice. Therefore your
प्रजुडिसिसिस से लड़ना है। इसलिए अपने
Give yourself enough space so that you can make mistakes
आपको इतना स्पेस भी दीजिए कि आप गलती
do. We are not the ones that you are in life
करेंगे। हम ये नहीं है कि आप जिंदगी में
Will always be politically correct. I am not
हमेशा पॉलिटिकली करेक्ट होंगे। मैं ना
Constantly turning this whole conversation into a
कास्टेंटली इस पूरे कॉन्वर्सेशन को एक
Scanning from a college student's perspective
कॉलेज स्टूडेंट के पर्सेक्टिव से स्कैन कर
I have been. sir what is why i am about
रहा हूं। सर व्हिच इज व्हाई आई एम अबाउट
To say what I'm about to say. Firstly
टू से व्हाट आई एम अबाउट टू से। पहले तो
I would like every listener, if possible, to
मैं चाहूंगा कि अगर हो सके तो हर लिसनर को
Nor should you carry a notebook. a pen and paper
ना एक नोटबुक लेनी चाहिए। एक पेन और पेपर
You should take it and yourself
लेना चाहिए और खुद
Five to 10 self-identifications
के पांच से 10 सेल्फ आइडेंटिफिकेशन
To list out the points. Right great. I
पॉइंट्स लिस्ट आउट करने। राइट ग्रेट। आई
Do it as an exercise in the classroom.
डू इट इट एज एन एक्सरसाइज इन द क्लासरूम।
I believe that throughout life, every three or four
मैं तो मानता हूं कि जिंदगी भर हर तीन-चार
You should do this for yourself once in a while. Two
सालों में ये करना चाहिए खुद के लिए। टू
Just see how you ideally every year. every year
जस्ट सी हाउ यू आइडियली एव्री ईयर। हर साल
You keep growing. In Your 20s Having a
आप ग्रो करते जाओ। इन योर 20ज पर हैविंग अ
Mirror is also an ancient skill. Right?
मिरर इज़ आल्सो एनेंट स्किल। राइट?
I am saying this because when I
मैं यह इसलिए कह रहा हूं क्योंकि जब मैं
I was 22 years old before YouTube, I was into fitness
22 साल का था YouTube से पहले मैं फिटनेस
I used to train and did fitness training
ट्रेनिंग करता था और फिटनेस ट्रेनिंग की
I used a 100 lbs. battery for a month before starting
शुरुआत से पहले मैंने एक महीने के लिए एक
In a relative's engineering factory
रिश्तेदार की इंजीनियरिंग की फैक्ट्री में
Work done. Good. Learned a lot there. Very
काम किया। गुड। बहुत कुछ सीखा वहां। बहुत
something about life ahh engineering
कुछ जिंदगी के बारे में अह कि इंजीनियरिंग
No blue collar person has such skills
जैसी स्किल भी ना कोई ब्लू कॉलर का इंसान
I can understand. That was my big learning that
समझ सकता है। दैट वाज़ माय बिग लर्निंग कि
Friend, if he has an engineering degree
यार अगर इन्होंने इंजीनियरिंग की डिग्री
If you understand engineering without taking it then that means
लिए बिना इंजीनियरिंग को समझा तो दैट मींस
Very high level skills can also be learned
वेरी हाई लेवल स्किल्स कैन आल्सो बी लर्नड
Very easily. it is I mean I know I am
वैरी ईजीली। इट इज़ आई मीन मैं आई नो आई एम
Interrupting here. But if I my
इंटरप्टिंग हियर। लेकिन मैं अगर अपनी
If I start with life, then my life
जिंदगी से शुरू करता हूं तो अपनी जिंदगी
A lot of learnings in the same way
की बहुत सारी लर्निंग्स इन द सेम वे मैं
Maybe the audience might not even know. I
शायद दर्शकों को ना भी मालूम हो। मैंने
I teach literature at the university.
मैं लिटरेचर पढ़ाता हूं यूनिवर्सिटी में
But before that I studied engineering and
लेकिन उससे पहले मैंने इंजीनियरिंग की और
I came after studying electrical engineering.
मैं इलेक्ट्रिकल इंजीनियरिंग करके आया था।
so I worked in a factory like you said
तो मैंने एक फैक्ट्री में जैसे आपने कहा
I did an engineering course in a factory
मैंने एक फैक्ट्री में इंजीनियरिंग एक
Worked as an engineer. yes and there
इंजीनियर के तौर पर काम किया। जी और वहां
But I had a workforce of around 20-25
पर मेरे पास एक वर्कफोर्स थी अराउंड 20-25
There was a small factory of people
लोगों की और एक छोटी सी फैक्ट्री थी
In which these people used to make press. Joe Light
जिसमें ये लोग प्रेस बनाते थे। जो लाइट
They used to make weight iron. in 2025
वेट आयरन होती है ना वो बनाते थे। इन 2025
Those three months spent with the workers
मजदूरों के साथ बिताए हुए वो तीन महीने
I worked in this factory
जिनमें मैंने इस फैक्ट्री में काम किया
Was. I learned from every single one of them
था। मैंने उनमें से हर एक व्यक्ति से सीखा
And surprisingly, I learned such things.
और हैरानी की बात है कि ऐसीऐसी चीजें सीखी
about which you neither have any
जिनके बारे में ना तो आपको आपकी
Actually, she was teaching you engineering, right?
इंजीनियरिंग सिखा रही थी ना आपको दरअसल
The society was teaching. Because you have in mind
सोसाइटी सिखा रही थी। क्योंकि आपको मन में
So there was prejudice, right? For example, all of us
तो प्रेजुडिसिस थे ना। मसलन हम सारी
The world used to believe this. I give you a
दुनिया ये मानकर चलती थी। मैं आपको एक
I am telling the story. That will make sense.
किस्सा बता रहा हूं। उससे समझ में आएगा।
It was always taught that you should give your worker
हमेशा से सिखाया जाता था कि वर्कर को आप
Throw money and they will do more work. Big
पैसा फेंके वो ज्यादा काम करेंगे। बड़ी
It was a simple thing and hence it was normal
सिंपल सी बात थी और इसलिए ये नॉर्मल
The pattern was that you counted the pieces at the end
पैटर्न था कि आपने एंड में पीस गिने
Will go. How many have you made and based on that
जाएंगे। आपने कितने बनाए हैं और उसके आधार
But you will get wedges. and I thought that if
पर आपको वेजेस मिलेंगे। एंड आई थॉट कि अगर
You can say that you make 100 at one place
आप ये कहें कि भ आप 100 बनाते हैं एक जगह
Make it 150. If you get it, production will increase
150 बनाइए। आपको मिलेंगे तो प्रोडक्शन बढ़
Should go. and i realise it doesnt work
जाना चाहिए। एंड आई रियलाइज़ इट डजंट वर्क
Like that. I was very surprised. I
लाइक दैट। मुझे बड़ी हैरानी हुई। मैंने
Said friend you have been told that if you score 150
कहा यार आपको कहा गया है कि अगर आप 150
If you make it then let's say you have ₹1000 right now
बनाएंगे तो अभी आपको मान लीजिए ₹1000
If you get it then you will get 1500. then you
मिलता है तब आपको 1500 मिलेगा। फिर आप
Why are you not doing it? all quiet. Then I
क्यों नहीं कर रहे हो? सब चुप। फिर मैंने
Tried to identify. So a worker
आइडेंटिफाई करने की कोशिश की। तो एक वर्कर
Whose name was Jiyalal. Jiyalal Used
था जिसका नाम था जियाालाल। जियाालाल यूज्ड
To be kind of a leader of that. of the leader
टू बी काइंड ऑफ़ अ लीडर ऑफ दैट। लीडर का
Meaning, understand a little about the union value
मतलब है एक छोटी सी समझिए यूनियन मान
Take it, if they needed it then they would
लीजिए कि जरूरत उनको जरूरत पड़ती थी तो वो
He used to come to us. Sir, do this work. I
हमारे पास आते थे। सर ये काम कर। मैंने
Jiyal was called and asked from jail
जियााल को बुलाया और जेल से पूछा जियााल
What is the reason for working? she gave me a
क्या वजह है कामने की? उसने मुझे एक
Gave the message of a wonderful life. he said sir
शानदार जिंदगी का संदेश दिया। उसने कहा सर
If I say that our
मैं अगर यह कहूं कि हमारी
The team will make 150 irons daily. It's price
टीम 150 आयरन रोज बनाएगी। इसकी कीमत
Three people lost their jobs in paying the bills
चुकाने में तीन लोगों की नौकरी चली
will go. because in fact what has happened in the last 20 years
जाएगी। क्योंकि दरअसल जो पिछले 20 साल का
My understanding tells me this. right now
मेरा मेरी समझ बताती है बताती है। अभी तो
You need 1500 Iron. But the truth is this
आपको चाहिए 1500 आयरन। लेकिन सच्चाई यह है
that the lean season will come and in the lean season we
कि लीन लीन सीजन आएगा और लीन सीजन में हम
So you must be making it with the same practice. So
तो उसी प्रैक्टिस से बना रहे होंगे। तो
The owner will find it easiest to choose three of these
मालिक को सबसे आसान लगेगा कि इनमें से तीन
Fire the people. of those three people
लोगों को निकाल दीजिए। उन तीन लोगों की
To save jobs it is important that we
नौकरी बचाने के लिए जरूरी है कि हम लोग
work at the same pace as we do
उसी गति से काम करें जिस गति से हम कर रहे
Are. I will definitely keep it to the minimum. I said
हैं। मिनिमम रख जरूर करेंगे। मैंने कहा
But why are you thinking so much about it now?
लेकिन अब इतनी बात की क्यों सोच रहे हो?
And this will make your life better. Then
और इससे तो आपकी जिंदगी बेहतर होगी। तब
He told another truth. he said sir you
उसने एक और सच्चाई बताई। उसने कहा सर आप
Give me 1000 or 1500. this country
मुझे 1000 दीजिए या 1500 दीजिए। इस देश
The life of a laborer is going to be like this
में मजदूर की जिंदगी होनी यह वाली है कि
I will go and sleep in a slum and go to the railway
मैं जाऊंगा झुग्गी में सोऊंगा और रेलवे
There was a line. There across the railway line
लाइन थी। वहां रेलवे लाइन के अक्रॉस
I will go and go to the toilet every morning.
जाकर रोज सुबह शौचालय जाने का काम करूंगा।
Ok? And I will come back. my life ₹500
ठीक है? और वापस आऊंगा। मेरी जिंदगी ₹500
It will not change from. effectively what i said
से नहीं बदलेगी। इफेक्टिवली व्हाट आई सेड
Is what I learned in management wasn't
इज़ व्हाट आई लर्नड इन मैनेजमेंट वाज़ंट
Functioning in the factory. it wasn't
फंक्शनिंग इन द फैक्ट्री। इट वाज़ंट
Functioning in the factory. and my judgement
फंक्शनिंग इन द फैक्ट्री। एंड माय जजमेंट
about the poor people that they have little money
अबाउट दी पुअर पीपल कि उनको थोड़ा सा पैसा
Give it. Now he will do anything. compared to him
दीजिए। अब वो कुछ भी कर लेंगे। उसकी तुलना
I am probably from middle class and upper class
में शायद मिडिल क्लास और अपपर क्लास
The person must be strangling his neighbor's friend
व्यक्ति जरूर अपने पड़ोसी का दोस्त का गला
He will survive in the competition. that person to those
काट लेगा कंपटीशन में। उस व्यक्ति को उन
There are three unnamed people who are worried about
अननेम्ड तीन लोगों की चिंता है जिसके बारे
I don't even know yet who will take it out
में अभी पता भी नहीं है कि कौन निकाले
We will know that if we adopt this strategy
जाएंगे कि अगर हमने एक ये स्ट्रेटजी अपनाई
Then we will be expelled. it changed my
तो हमें निकाले जाएंगे। इट चेंज्ड माय
Perspective a lot. Human Dynamics
पर्सेक्टिव अ लॉट। ह्यूमन डायनामिक्स
Exactly. I learnt it let a lot in
एक्जेक्टली। आई लर्न इट लेट अ लॉट लेट इन
Human Relations Approach to Management
मैनेजमेंट कि इसको ह्यूमन रिलेशंस अप्रोच
They say etcetera etcetera. but i learned
कहते हैं वगैरह-वगैरह। लेकिन आई लर्नर्ड
It's from a Jiyalal. we who was never
इट फ्रॉम अ जियालाल। हम हु वाज़ हुड नेवर
been to school at all and actually not if
बीन टू स्कूल एट ऑल एंड एक्चुअली ना अगर
This HR skill of yours tells people
आपकी यह जो एचआर वाली स्किल है लोगों को
If this skill is strong then it is always possible to manage
मैनेज करना अगर यह स्किल तगड़ी है इट ऑलवेज
Pay off in your career it's as I said it is
पेज़ ऑफ इन योर करियर इट्स एज आई सेड इट इज़
All About Getting Work Done I am a little bit
ऑल अबाउट गेटिंग वर्क डन मैं कुछ-कुछ
I would like to say things definitely this is a 32
चीजें कहना चाहूंगा डेफिनेटली ये एक 32
Year old is perspective and please add
ईयर ओल्ड का पर्सेक्टिव है एंड प्लीज ऐड
to it if you feel that something is missing
टू इट इफ यू फील दैट समथिंग इज मिसिंग
From my formula I meet many people
फ्रॉम माय फार्मूला मैं बहुत लोगों से
I have met through the show and met some great people
मिला हूं शो के थ्रू और दिग्गजों से मिला
yes, I have noticed some commonalities
हूं कुछ-कुछ कॉमनैलिटीज मैंने देखी है
There are so many successful people in any industry
जितने भी सफल लोग हैं किसी भी इंडस्ट्री
It can be cricket, it can be Bollywood, whatever
के क्रिकेट हो सकता है बॉलीवुड जो भी
One commonality among those businesses is that
बिजनेस उन सों में एक कॉमनैलिटी ये है कि
A in some perspective of his craft he
अ उनकी क्राफ्ट की किसी पर्सेक्टिव में वो
He is a specialist. they don't have to be great
स्पेशलिस्ट है। दे डोंट हैव टू बी ग्रेट
at all aspects of their craft but they
एट ऑल एस्पेक्ट्स ऑफ़ देयर क्राफ्ट बट दे
Are usually the best at one aspect. it
आर द यूजुअली द बेस्ट एट वन एस्पेक्ट। यह
This is the basis of growth. Basis of career growth.
बेसिस ऑफ़ ग्रोथ है। बेसिस ऑफ़ करियर ग्रोथ।
In second place is self-confidence. Self
दूसरे स्थान पर है अ आत्मविश्वास। सेल्फ
belief or confidence that you're going for it
बिलीफ या कॉन्फिडेंस कि गोइंग फॉर इट
Etc. Here I am talking about execution.
एटसेट्रा यहां मैं एग्जीक्यूशन की बात कर
I did not stay either, because I believe that
रहा भी नहीं क्योंकि मैं मानता हूं कि
Execution hard work is a very base level thing
एक्सजीक्यूशन मेहनत एक बहुत बेस लेवल चीज
Is. This must happen. This has to be it
है। ये तो होनी ही चाहिए। ये तो होनी ही
Needed Meaning this is not their place.
चाहिए। मतलब ये ये उनके स्थान पर नहीं है।
This is a must. other than that you are different
ये तो चाहिए ही चाहिए। उसके अलावा आप अलग
What qualities can you bring to this?
करने के लिए किन गुणों को ला सकते हैं?
Yes. So first and foremost that specialist
जी। तो फर्स्ट एंड फॉर्मस्ट वो स्पेशलिस्ट
In One Aspect of Craft. Seconds
इन वन एस्पेक्ट ऑफ क्राफ्ट। सेकंड
Confidence. But a third one is very underrated
कॉन्फिडेंस। पर एक थर्ड बहुत अंडररेटेड
The factor is that of maturity. and this is you
फैक्टर है मैच्योरिटी का। और यह आप
Actually can't work on it. I Feel
एक्चुअली इस पर काम नहीं कर सकते। आई फील
There are ways to improve it but it's time
देयर आर वेज़ टू इंप्रूव इट बट यह वक्त का
It is a gift. and it really adds an
एक तोहफा होता है। एंड इट रियली ऐड्स एन
To edge your career in the long term. Very
एज टू योर करियर इन द लॉन्ग टर्म। बहुत
There are all these people who actually attain maturity.
सारे ऐसे लोग हैं जो एक्चुअली मैच्योरिटी
I never chase anyone. Age N Time Mill
को कभी भी चज़ नहीं करते। एज एन वक्त मिल
It goes into the hands. The hands get the edge
जाता है हाथों में। एज मिल जाती है हाथों
But I don't get maturity. Perhaps their
में बट मैच्योरिटी नहीं मिलती। शायद उनके
because of the people around them, maybe
आसपास जो लोग हैं उनकी वजह से, शायद उनके
Whatever your priorities are in life,
खुद के प्रायोरिटीज जो भी है लाइफ में उन
Because of priorities, maybe
प्रायोरिटीज की वजह से, शायद
Because of distractions. Butt Maturity
डिस्ट्रैक्शंस की वजह से। बट मैच्योरिटी
There is a very big X factor in careers. I
इज अ वेरी बिग एक्स फैक्टर इन करियर्स। आई
feel that when something big happens in your life
फील कि जब आपकी लाइफ में कुछ ऐसे बड़े
Maturity even when accidents happen
हादसे हो जाते हैं तब भी मैच्योरिटी
There is an increase. From Wrigley. butt what are you
इनक्रीस होती है। राइटली से। बट आप क्या
What would you like to say about my algorithm?
कहना चाहोगे मेरे इस एल्गोरिदम के बारे
In? usually what you said isn't it time
में? आमतौर पर जो आपने कहा ना कि यह समय
It is something that comes with time. In the country
बीतने के साथ आने वाली बात है। देश में
How many 32 year olds can understand this?
कितने 32 साल के युवा होंगे जो इस बात को
you could say it, you could feel it, or
कह सकते होंगे, महसूस कर सकते होंगे या
You must have understood. Just try to understand this
समझ पाए होंगे। जरा इस बात को समझने की
Let's try. This is what you have collected hundreds of
कोशिश करते हैं। यह जो आपने सैकड़ों
I've got podcasts from you wonderful people
पडकास्ट लिए हैं, आप शानदार लोगों से
meet constantly
लगातार मिले
Are. This gave you the idea of ​​how to do that algorithm.
हैं। इसने आपको वह उस उस एल्गोरिथम को के
that inside you
लिए एक्सपोज किया है कि आपके अंदर
This understanding was able to create this vision that you could see
यह समझ यह नजर पैदा हो पाई कि आप देख पाए
that there is such a thing as maturity which
कि एक चीज ऐसी भी है मैच्योरिटी नाम की जो
That it can only come from this type of contact.
कि इसी किस्म के संपर्क से ही आ सकती है।
This can come only from this companionship. That means someone else
इस सहचर्य से ही आ सकती है। यानी किसी और
what did he do in his life? you from him
ने अपनी जिंदगी में क्या किया? आप उससे
Keep a dog to learn from, not yourself every time
सीखने की कुत रखें ना कि खुद ही हर बार
You need those accidents in your life
आपको अपनी जिंदगी में ही वह हादसे चाहिए
that you will be able to learn. where is this coming from
कि आप सीख पाएंगे। यह कहां से आ पा रहा
Is? This comes from the fact that your
है? यह इस बात से आ पा रहा है कि आपके
There is that maturity inside you to know that
अंदर वो मैच्योरिटी है कि आप जान सके कि
For experience and ability to learn every time
अनुभव और सीखने की क्षमता के लिए हर बार
It is not necessary to go through the tragedy yourself.
खुद त्रासदी से गुजरना जरूरी नहीं है।
However, despite that, there are some difficulties in life
हालांकि उसके बावजूद जिंदगी में दो चार
Tragedies are bound to happen. There will be a couple of crises
त्रासदियां होंगी ही। दो चार संकट आएंगे
Whatever I will teach, and that too at my own pace
ही जो सिखाएंगे ही और वो अपनी गति से
Will come. If you are more popular. If
आएंगे। अगर आप ज्यादा लोकप्रिय हैं। अगर
If you work hard then more
आप ज्यादा मेहनत कर रहे हैं तो ज्यादा
Will come. But that is a different matter. main
आएंगे। लेकिन वो एक अन्यथा बात है। मुख्य
The point is whether you care about other people's lives
बात यह है कि क्या आप दूसरों की जिंदगी के
Are you ready to learn from experience or not?
अनुभव से सीखने को तैयार हैं कि नहीं?
Like you have taken hundreds of podcasts. I
जैसे सैकड़ों पडकास्ट आपने ली हैं। मैंने
I have also met those students regularly
भी लगातार उन विद्यार्थियों से मिला हूं
Those who give interview, clear the mains
जो इंटरव्यू देते हैं, मेंस क्लियर करते
Yes, he comes for interview. ah i think
हैं, इंटरव्यू देने आते हैं। अ मुझे लगता
That's what I learned from them. I
है कि मैं मैंने उनकीयों से सीखा है। मैं
I often give this example. I don't
अक्सर इस एग्जांपल को देता हूं। मुझे नहीं
Find out if you will be able to connect it or not.
पता कि आप इसे कनेक्ट कर पाएंगे कि नहीं।
But suppose if you look at this table.
लेकिन मान लीजिए अगर आप इस टेबल को देखें।
This is a wooden replica of this table. Correct
इस टेबल को यह लकड़ी का रेप्लिका है। ठीक
Isn't it? Cut some stems horizontally
है ना? किसी किसी तने को हॉरिजॉन्टल काटा
Gaya is its replica and it has lines
गया उसका रेप्लिका है और इसमें लाइनें
which is visible in If You Remember
दिखाई दे रही हैं जो कि अगर इफ यू रिमेंबर
So what are these tree rings of every tree?
तो क्या है ये ट्री रिंग्स है हर पेड़ का
The tree rings and I've been talking
ट्री रिंग होता है एंड आई हैव बीन टॉकिंग
about it a lot as a metaphor and as a
अबाउट इट अ लॉट एक मेटाफर की तरह भी और एक
How does it come inside him like life
जिंदगी की तरह भी कैसे आता है उसके अंदर
Think about tree rings and see the life of that tree
ट्री रिंग सोच के देखिए उस पेड़ की जिंदगी
what happened in that tree ring came which
में क्या हुआ कि ट्री रिंग आया जिसने
Had I ever studied even a little biology or botany?
थोड़ी सी भी बायोलॉजी पढ़ी थी कभी बॉटनी
He had read that every year a tree
पढ़ी थी वो जानता है कि हर साल एक ट्री
The ring comes and after a whole year has passed its
रिंग आता है एक पूरा साल बीतता है तो उसका
A layer forms on the stem which
जो तना है उस पर एक लेयर चढ़ जाती है जो
Later, if it is cut like this, then
बाद में अगर उसको ऐसे काटा जाएगा तो
It will come like a tree. Now just give it a little
ट्रीिंग की तरह आएगी। अब जरा इसे थोड़ा
Think seriously about maturity
गंभीरता से सोचिए उसे मैच्योरिटी वाली चीज
It will immediately unfold itself. this which
एकदम अपने आप को अनफोल्ड करेगी। ये जो
Treeing is one year treeing, suppose
ट्रीिंग है एक साल का ट्रीिंग मान लीजिए
It has 50 treeings so it means tree
इसमें 50 ट्रेिंग है तो इसका मतलब है पेड़
The age of the crypt is 50 years. yes its every
क्रिप्ट की उम्र 50 साल है। जी इसका हर
Treeing represents a year. and that
ट्रीिंग एक साल को बताता है। और वो
Any good botanist can tell by looking at the trees
ट्रीिंग देखकर कोई भी अच्छा बॉटनिस्ट बता
It is possible that this tree will be cut this year
सकता है कि इस साल में इस पेड़ को
What all I had to endure. wow did the flood come or not
क्या-क्या सहना पड़ा। वाह बाढ़ आई कि नहीं
I? Is it okay? Was there a drought? Fertilizer
आई? ठीक है ना? सूखा पड़ा था क्या? खाद
Did you get it or not? or somebody somewhere
मिली थी कि नहीं मिली थी? या कहीं कोई
Did you not get any illness? All of this is recorded
बीमारी तो नहीं आई थी? ये सब का सब दर्ज
It will happen in that one year of treeing. Right?
हो जाएगा उस एक साल के ट्रीिंग में। राइट?
And year after year they will continue to grow into trees. If
और साल दर साल वो ट्रीिंग बनते जाएंगे। इफ
You are a good reader of these trees. You
यू आर अ गुड रीडर ऑफ दीज़ ट्रीिंग्स। यू
can read the 50 years personality of this
कैन रीड द 50 इयर्स पर्सनालिटी ऑफ दिस
Tree. Provided you are a good reader. To you
ट्री। प्रोवाइडेड यू आर अ गुड रीडर। आपको
Must be a good read. then you
एक अच्छा पढ़ने वाला होना चाहिए। तब आप
You can read and understand what that tree has suffered
पढ़ सकते हैं और उस पेड़ ने जो जो सहा वह
Everything can contribute to your life
सब आपकी जिंदगी को कंट्रीब्यूट कर सकता
Is. And this is what maturity is
है। एंड दिस इज व्हाट मैच्योरिटी इज हम
Being non judgemental that year this tree
बीइंग नॉन जजमेंटल उस साल ये वाला ट्रीिंग
Why is it thin? Oh brother, that year it dried up
पतला क्यों है? अरे भाई उस साल उसको सूखा
It was lying there. Water not available, nutrition not available
पड़ा था। नहीं मिला पानी पोषण नहीं मिला
That's why this happened. in this tree this one
इसलिए ऐसा हो गया। इस ट्री में इस वाले
Why did this lump appear on the tree?
पेड़ में ये गांठ क्यों दिखाई दिया?
Illness had arrived. The tree was fighting disease.
बीमारी आई थी। पेड़ बीमारी से लड़ रहा था।
That's why it appeared inside him. As such
इसलिए उसके अंदर ये दिखाई दिया। ऐसा
It will happen with humans. brother Ranveer's
इंसानों के साथ होगा। भाई रणवीर की
This lump is visible in the personality.
पर्सनालिटी में ये गांठ दिखाई दे रही है।
Why did you come? Or I could be judgemental
क्यों आई? या तो मैं जजमेंटल हो सकता हूं
Or it is Ranveer's life too. very bad man
या रणवीर की जिंदगी भी है। बहुत बुरा आदमी
Is. He is a good man. whichever one or the other
है। अच्छा आदमी है। व्हाटएवर या दूसरा
The way could be that I am non judgemental.
तरीका हो सकता है कि मैं नॉन जजमेंटल हूं।
Because I know that every person
क्योंकि मैं जानता हूं कि हर व्यक्ति के
Our personalities also have rings
हम लोगों की पर्सनालिटी के भी तो टरिंग्स
That which is visible. so i will look at
है ना जो दिखाई दे रहे हैं। तो मैं देखूं
and should I say no this year or this month or
और यह कहूं कि नहीं इस साल या इस महीने या
In this part of life, a certain person
जिंदगी के इस हिस्से में अमुक व्यक्ति ने
This thing was true which was visible in his personality
यह चीज सही थी जो उसकी पर्सनालिटी में दिख
It has been happening. Because if you know this thing
रही है। क्योंकि आपके आप अगर इस बात को
are able to read that a certain person's
पढ़ पा रहे हैं कि अमुक व्यक्ति के
You will know what is in your personality
व्यक्तित्व में क्या है तो आपको पता होगा
What work can you do with it
कि किस कौन सा काम आप इससे करा सकते हैं
And which work is not wise to get done?
और कौन सा काम कराना इससे समझदारी नहीं
Is. At the end of the day success is all about
है। एट द एंड ऑफ़ द डे सक्सेस इज़ ऑल अबाउट
Getting work done. success is all about
गेटिंग वर्क डन। सक्सेस इज़ ऑल अबाउट
Getting Work
गेटिंग वर्क
Done. But the work isn't down to just that
डन। बट द वर्क इज़ नॉट डाउन टू जस्ट
Execution. No it is not with art
एग्जीक्यूशन। नो इट इज नॉट कला के साथ
Have to do it. Not just to do with art.
करना है। सिर्फ कला के साथ ही नहीं करना।
Execution: Maybe you created systems
एग्जीक्यूशन तो शायद आपने सिस्टम्स बना
If you give it will happen. But
दिए तो हो भी जाएगा। लेकिन
originality
ओरिजिनलिटी
Originality is the responsibility of the one who
मौलिकता वो जिम्मेदारी उसी की है जिसका
There is work. He is the only one who can bring it. You have your one
काम है। वही ला सकता है। आपने अपना एक
Did the ideation. You made up an idea. and that
आइडिएशन किया। आपने एक विचार बनाया। और वह
Or it will remain only at the level of thought.
या तो केवल विचार के स्तर पर रह जाएगा।
Let's enjoy that too. honestly i this
चलिए उसका भी आनंद है। ऑनेस्टली मैं यह
I do not believe that when all the ideas come down to earth
नहीं मानता कि सारे विचार जब जमीन पर आ
They are useful only when they go. the moment when
जाते हैं तभी काम के होते हैं। जिस क्षण
You created a joy came to you at that very moment.
आपने रचा एक आनंद तो आपको उसी समय आ गया।
But when you see it in a tangible form,
लेकिन जब आप उसे एक मूर्त रूप में देखते
He has a different kick after execution
हैं एग्जीक्यूशन के बाद उसका एक अलग किक
Is. Whatever we have talked about and come
है। जो कुछ भी बातें हमने करी है और आई
feel it's very very useful for a young
फील इट्स वेरी वेरी यूज़फुल फॉर अ यंग
Professional. even if they don't understand
प्रोफेशनल। इवन इफ दे नॉट अंडरस्टैंडिंग
It's on the surface level.
इट ऑन द सरफेस लेवल।
These thoughts sit in their minds and turn into trees.
यह थॉट्स उनके दिमाग में बैठकर पेड़ बन
I will go one day. that's what i feel which
जाएंगे एक दिन। दैट्स व्हाट आई फील व्हिच
is why come back to that practical
इज व्हाई कम बैक टू दैट प्रैक्टिकल
Exercise. because one of my aunts said this
एक्सरसाइज। क्योंकि ये मेरी एक मासी ने
taught me that if you are 22 years old
मुझे सिखाया था कि यार अगर आप 22 साल के
and you yourself don't know what to do in your career
हो और खुद पता नहीं कि करियर में क्या
Have to do it. Or if you have five UPSC
करना है। या अगर आपके पांच यूपीएससी के
The attempts are over. Same Position
अटेम्प्ट खत्म हो चुके हैं। सेम पोजीशन
lost but with
लॉस्ट बट विद
Data
डाटा
Points.
पॉइंट्स।
Ah I feel I should buy a paper. from five
अह आई फील कि एक पेपर लेना चाहिए। पांच से
10 self identification points of yourself
10 सेल्फ आइडेंटिफिकेशन पॉइंट्स खुद के
You should write about personality. That
पर्सनैलिटी के बारे में लिखने चाहिए। कि
I am this, I am this, I am this. at the same time
मैं यह हूं, यह हूं, यह हूं। एट द सेम
Three such strengths should be written down once a day. That
टाइम तीन ऐसे स्ट्रेंथ्स लिखने चाहिए। कि
These three things probably made my career
इन तीन चीजों की वजह से शायद मेरा करियर
can move forward. When I was 22 years old,
आगे बढ़ सकता है। जब मैं 22 साल का था,
My three strengths that I listed out
मेरे थ्री स्ट्रेंथ्स जो मैंने लिस्ट आउट
What he did was fitness and communication
करे थे वो थे, फिटनेस, अ कम्युनिकेशन
skills, and marketing. Marketing to me
स्किल्स, और मार्केटिंग। मुझे मार्केटिंग
I understood that because there was a lot of marketing
की समझ थी कि क्योंकि मार्केटिंग की बहुत
Had done all the internships. personality
सारी इंटर्नशिप्स किए थे। पर्सनालिटी
was good in college and was very fit and
अच्छी थी कॉलेज में भी और बहुत फिट था और
I also did a fitness course. So
मैंने फिटनेस का कोर्स भी किया था। तो
There was an understanding of fitness science. those three things
फिटनेस साइंस की एक समझ थी। उन तीन चीजों
I sat with the
को लेकर मैं बैठा
I thought about it and eventually I decided that yes
सोचा और इवेंचुअली आई डिसाइडेड कि यार हां
Maybe I can become a fitness YouTuber. Correct
मे बी आई कैन बिकम अ फिटनेस यूट्यूबर। ठीक
Is. Started a fitness YouTube channel. There
है। फिटनेस YouTube की शुरुआत करी। वहां
From became a fashion youtuber. Great. Fashion
से फैशन यूट्यूबर बन गए। ग्रेट। फैशन
From YouTuber to podcaster again.
यूट्यूबर से फिर पॉडकास्टर बनेंगे।
Definitely have a nice journey. and podcaster
डेफिनेटली हैव अ नाइस जर्नी। और पॉडकास्टर
After being made now we are going moving on to the
बनने के बाद अब वी आर गो मूविंग ऑन टू द
Next stage. which will also be about
नेक्स्ट स्टेज। व्हिच विल आल्सो बी अबाउट
Business YouTube. But that is the beginning
बिज़नेस YouTube। पर उसकी शुरुआत तो वो
It was done through paper. Ok? and this same paper,
पेपर से हुई थी। ठीक है? और इसी पेपर,
Notebook,
नोटबुक,
This is what Penn is trying to highlight
पेन इसी को हाईलाइट करने की कोशिश कर रहा
yes for the audience. that friend do this
हूं ऑडियंस के लिए। कि यार ये करो ये
Do exercise. At the beginning of his career
एक्सरसाइज करो। करियर की शुरुआत में
Write three or four strains of your own. But every year
तीन-चार स्ट्रेंस लिखो खुद के। पर हर साल
10 selfies with a pen and paper
एक पेन और पेपर लेकर 10 सेल्फ
Write down the identification points, especially the
आइडेंटिफिकेशन पॉइंट्स लिख दो एस्पेशली द
Negative things that make you feel embarrassed
नेगेटिव वंस जिसकी वजह से आप शर्मिंदा हो
The things you judge by are your weaknesses
जो आपके वीकनेसेस हैं द थिंग्स यू जज
Yourself
योरसेल्फ
about variant i think it's actually a
अबाउट वेरीेंट आई थिंक इट्स एक्चुअली अ
life long process it is it is but it is
लाइफ लॉन्ग प्रोसेस इट इज इट इज़ बट इट्स
not just that i mean there is a different
नॉट जस्ट दैट आई मीन देयर इज़ अ डिफरेंट
version of it which i do in the class cool
वर्जन ऑफ़ इट व्हिच आई डू इन द क्लास कुल
If we understand this properly by combining it with our
मिला के अगर इसको ढंग से समझे कि हम आपने
He said that we have some weaknesses.
कहा कि हमारी कुछ कमजोरी ोरियां होती हैं।
Yes and we have some strengths. These
जी और हमारी कुछ स्ट्रेंथ्स होती हैं। ये
Normally this is what we call corporates
नॉर्मली ये वही है जिसे हम कॉर्पोरेट्स
I do it too. Sort Analysis,
में भी करते हैं। सॉर्ट एनालिसिस,
Strength, weakness etc. butt of humans
स्ट्रेंथ, वीकनेस वगैरह। बट इंसानों की
Sort analysis takes place. be technical
सॉर्ट एनालिसिस होती है। टेक्निकली हो
It can. But I'll take it one step further
सकती है। लेकिन मैं इसको और एक स्टेप आगे
I am going to ask. For the last 22 years I have been
जाके पूछ रहा हूं। पिछले 22 साल से मैं ये
I am working on taking interviews. Mock
इंटरव्यूज लेने का काम कर रहा हूं। मॉक
Interviews in which people appear for main exam
इंटरव्यूज जिसमें कि लोग मेंस एग्जाम
Let me clear it. then come in front of me
क्लियर करते हैं। उसके बाद मेरे सामने आते
Are. we people i mean in front of us
हैं। हम लोग मेरे मतलब हम लोगों के सामने
They come and we take the interview. And
आते हैं और हम लोग इंटरव्यू लेते हैं। और
Based on that, this is my understanding
उसके आधार पर मेरी जो समझ बनी है वो ये है
that if we understand from this principle who is successful
कि अगर हम इस सिद्धांत से समझे कि कौन सफल
Who succeeded and who did not? In between these
हुआ और कौन सफल नहीं हुआ? इनके बीच के
Are the differences based only on individual traits?
अंतर क्या केवल इंडिविजुअल ट्रेट्स के
Are there differences? Differences in Individual Qualities
अंतर हैं? इंडिविजुअल क्वालिटीज के अंतर
Or is there a bigger difference than that? like you did
हैं या ये उससे ज्यादा अंतर है? जैसे आपने
I told you there are some things, that is the base.
कहा था ना कुछ चीजें हैं वह तो बेस है।
Like hard work is fine, hard work has to be done.
जैसे मेहनत ठीक है मेहनत करनी ही करनी है।
No one will be successful without hard work. Ok
बिना मेहनत के कोई सफल नहीं होगा। ठीक है
No? Hard work, commitment and dedication is required. Correct
ना? मेहनत चाहिए, कमिटमेंट लगन चाहिए। ठीक
Isn't it? and individual trades that occur
है ना? और इंडिविजुअल ट्रेड्स जो होते हैं
Rest of the CF but is this a thing to be in itself
बाकी सीएफ लेकिन क्या ये होना अपने आप में
is the differentiating factor. unfortunately
डिफरेंशिएटिंग फैक्टर है। अनफॉर्चुनेटली
no because all the people or most of the people
नहीं है क्योंकि सारे लोग या अधिकांश लोग
You are keeping these trades, right? Brother
इन ट्रेड्स को तो रख ही रहे हैं ना। भाई
I am preparing for UPSC
यूपीएससी की तैयारी करने वाला मैं
I am coming to UPSC but this is not all
यूपीएससी पे हर आ रहा हूं लेकिन ये हर चीज
Will be applicable on . to prepare for UPSC
पे लागू होगा। यूपीएससी पे तैयारी करने
Every person knows that hard work is necessary
वाला हर व्यक्ति को पता ही है ना मेहनत
Will have to do it. He is working hard for 810 hours
करनी पड़ेगी। वो 810 घंटे मेहनत कर रहा
Is. The commitment is already showing. away from home
है। कमिटमेंट दिखा ही रहा है। घर से दूर
He is coming and staying here. The dedication is already showing. Dream
आके रह रहा है। लगन दिखा ही रहा है। सपना
He already has it. Is it okay? Everything is there.
उसके पास है ही। ठीक है ना? सब कुछ है।
But unfortunately everyone has it.
लेकिन अनफॉर्चूनेटलीकि ये सबके पास है।
So any of these differentiating factors
इसलिए इनमें से कुछ भी डिफरशिएटिंग फैक्टर
does not survive. hum because everybody is doing the
नहीं बचता। हम बिकॉज़ एवरीबॉडी इस डूइंग द
Same thing. Every person is working hard. every
सेम थिंग। हर व्यक्ति मेहनत कर रहा है। हर
The person is showing dedication. every person
व्यक्ति लगन दिखा रहा है। हर व्यक्ति
Showing commitment. Things like that.
कमिटमेंट दिखा रहा है। थिंग्स लाइक दैट।
So what are the differentiating factors?
सो व्हाट आर द डिफरेंशिएटिंग फैक्टर्स?
one carefully and I will give this to the class
एक ध्यान से और इसको मैं क्लास में
I do exercise. I say that this is
एक्सरसाइज करता हूं। मैं यह कहता हूं कि
It is up to you whether you succeed or fail
आपका सफल होना या असफल होना यह सही है कि
All these things are required in this. but this big
इसमें यह सारी चीजें चाहिए। लेकिन इस बड़ी
These are minor variables in the equation.
इक्वेशन में यह माइनर वेरिएबल्स हैं।
Unfortunately I am saying unfortunately.
दुर्भाग्य से दुर्भाग्य कह रहा हूं।
Unfortunately the major variables are in your hands
दुर्भाग्य से मेजर वेरिएबल्स आपके हाथ में
Not there. What are those variables? that is
नहीं है। वो वेरिएबल्स क्या हैं? वो है
What are your privileges? And your
आपके प्रिविलेजेस क्या हैं? और आपके
What are deprivations? Is it okay? where are you
डेप्रिवेशंस क्या हैं? ठीक है ना? आप कहां
Were born? Which was your school? on your own
पैदा हुए? आपका स्कूल कौन सा था? आपके आप
The family you were born in
जिस परिवार में पैदा हुए उसमें आपके
What did dad do? who has them
पिताजी क्या करते थे? उनके उनके पास कौन
From what privileges were available? Which ones
से प्रिविलेजेस अवेलेबल थे? कौन से
Were there resources? did you go to IIT or Changmal
रिसोर्सेज थे? आप आईआईटी में गए या चंगामल
Went to inter college. All This Gonna Matter
इंटर कॉलेज में गए। ऑल दिस गोना मैटर
Because there are the social structure. so there
बिकॉज़ देयर आर द सोशल स्ट्रक्चर। तो देयर
our privileges and similarly they are
आर प्रिविलेजेस एंड सिमिलरली दे आर
Departures. This is what I say in class
डेप्रवेशंस। मैं ये कहता हूं जो क्लास में
I exercise with my kids
एक्सरसाइज करता हूं अपने बच्चों से कि भ
Identify your 10 identity markers.
अपनी 10 आइडेंटिटीज मार्कर्स को पहचानिए।
In the Same Way as You Say the Strength to Me
इन द सेम वे एज़ यू से द स्ट्रेंथ को
Recognize. 10 Identity Markers You Know
पहचानिए। 10 आइडेंटिटी मार्कर्स आपका आप
Which class do you come from? Financial
आप कौन से वर्ग से आते हैं? फाइनेंसियल
The situation is yours. which area do you come from
सिचुएशन आपकी है। कौन से क्षेत्र से आते
Are? What is your religion? your race
हैं? आपका धर्म क्या है? आपकी जाती है
Etc. etc. you can create your 10 identities
वगैरह-वगैरह आप अपने 10 आइडेंटिटी
Identify the markers. what is your language
मार्कर्स पहचान दीजिए। आपकी लैंग्वेज कौन
is it c? do you know english or not
सी है? आपको अंग्रेजी आती है कि नहीं आती
Is. Is it okay? marker and beyond
है। ठीक है ना? मार्कर और उसके आगे सिर्फ
Write whether he is privileged or
ये लिखिए कि वो प्रिविलेज्ड है या
He is deprived. let's have it in
डिप्र्राइव्ड है। लेट्स लेट्स हैव इन टू
Categories only. Is it okay? Obviously I
कैटेगरीज ओनली। ठीक है ना? ऑब्वियसली आई
No it's a spectrum. but it is easy to
नो इट्स अ स्पेक्ट्रम। लेकिन इट इज़ इजी टू
Identify whether you are privileged or not
आइडेंटिफाई कि भ आप प्रिविलज्ड हैं कि मान
So what is your language? So you say that
लीजिए आपकी भाषा क्या है? तो आप कहें कि
You come from an English-speaking family
आप एक अंग्रेजी बोलने वाले परिवार से आते
Are. You are good in English. so you
हैं। यू आर गुड इन इंग्लिश। तो आप
Are privileged. and you say no
प्रिविलेज्ड हैं। और आप कहें कि नहीं जी
I only know Bhojpuri so you are
मुझे तो केवल भोजपुरी आती है तो यू आर
Dipped. Right? You did not do this society
डिप्ड। राइट? आपने नहीं किया ये सोसाइटी
has done it. But on the basis of this, just look at these
ने किया है। लेकिन इसके बेसिस पर जरा इनकी
Make a list of these 10. Out of these 10
लिस्ट बनाइए इन 10 की। इन 10 में से
In front of how many have you written P Privilege
कितनों के आगे आपने पी प्रिविलेज लिखा है
And how many have deprivation written in front of them?
और कितनों के आगे डेप्रिवेशन लिखा है उसे
Count it. and then please work on each off
काउंट कीजिए। एंड देन प्लीज वर्क ऑन ईच ऑफ
It. if it is a privilege and I am
इट। इफ इट इज़ अ प्रिविलेज एंड आई एम
Making a point here. if it is a
मेकिंग अ पॉइंट हियर। इफ इट इज़ अ
Privilege then you have to work to
प्रिविलेज देन यू हैव टू वर्क टू
Transients that privilege. You have to do this for your
ट्रांजेंट दैट प्रिविलेज। आपको अपने इस जो
You have the privilege because you are a man
आपको सुविधा मिली है क्योंकि आप पुरुष की
I was born like this because I was born in a rich family
तरह पैदा हुए क्योंकि अमीर घर में पैदा
because you need to go to an English school
हुए क्योंकि आपके आपको अंग्रेजी के स्कूल
sent in etc etc then you have to do this
में भेजा गया वगैरह-वगैरह तो आपको यह करना
in the next one year that you will get this
है अगले एक साल में कि आपको यह जो
We had received privileges and they have to be encroached upon.
प्रिविलेज मिले थे इनका अतिक्रमण करना है।
you have to go by
यू हैव टू गो बिय्ड
this and if it deprives you,
दिस और अगर यह आपके डिप्र्राइव्ड है,
Deprivation is more than you have to work to
डेप्रिवेशन से है देन यू हैव टू वर्क टू
Overcome this. Not always in your hand. so it
ओवरकम दिस। नॉट ऑलवेज इन योर हैंड। सो इट
will it take its going to be a long life
विल टेक इट्स गोइंग टू बी अ लॉन्ग लाइफ
Long project. Is it okay? our country
लॉन्ग प्रोजेक्ट। ठीक है ना? हमारे देश
In many cases I work my whole life
में तो कई मामलों में पूरी जिंदगी काम
Even after doing this, you can not use that privilege
करने के बाद भी आप उस प्रिविलज को उस
Can't complete the deprivation that you need
डिप्रवेशन को पूरा नहीं कर सकते जो आपको
Got it from birth. but still work on
जन्म से से मिली। लेकिन फिर भी वर्क ऑन
Dec. If you are able to work on these two
दिस। इफ यू आर एबल टू वर्क ऑन दीज़ टू
things it is going to be more than
थिंग्स इट इज़ गोइंग टू बी मोरेंट देन
Working on individual trades as you can.
वर्किंग ऑन इंडिविजुअल ट्रेड्स एस यू सेड।
And this is how it works. Trust Me It Works.
एंड दिस इट वर्क्स। ट्रस्ट मी इट वर्क्स।
because i have seen this in my life
क्योंकि मैंने अपनी जिंदगी में देखा यह
It works. I'm sure I did that
काम करता है। आई एम श्योर मैंने मैं ऐसे
I have met students whose lives
विद्यार्थियों से मिला हूं जिनकी जिंदगी
I work in. So I hope so
में काम करता है। तो मैं उम्मीद करता हूं
that work in the life of many people
कि बहुत सारे लोगों की जिंदगी में काम
Will do it. We have basically covered three exercises
करेगा। हमने बेसिकली तीन एक्सरसाइज को
The list has been got out. First exercise three
लिस्ट आउट करा है। पहली एक्सरसाइज तीन
Put out the strength list. Right? by the force of
स्ट्रेंथ लिस्ट आउट कर दो। राइट? जिसके बल
But I want to make my own career.
पर खुद का करियर बनाना चाह रहा हूं।
weaknesses then 10 these privileges or
वीकनेसेस फिर 10 ये प्रिविलेज या
Deprivation points. Right? that where you from
डेप्रिवेशन पॉइंट्स। राइट? कि आप कहां से
Have you come? Etsetra Etsetra. End
आए हो। एटसेट्रा एटसेट्रा। एंड
Unfortunately, for some people, 10s
अनफॉर्चूनेटली कुछ-कुछ लोगों के लिए 10ों
Point depreciation occurred. yes here privilege
पॉइंट डिप्रिशन हुआ। हां यहां प्रिविलज
Privilege happened here. and unfortunately
यहां प्रिविलेज हुआ। एंड अनफॉर्चुनेटली
both its a sad story both ways
दोनों इट्स इट्स अ सेड स्टोरी बोथ वेज़
Trust me. This is the reality of India. yes this
ट्रस्ट मी। ये भारत की असलियत है। हां ये
This is the reality of India. I am in my class
भारत की असलियत है। मैं अपनी क्लास में
I teach such girls. we are the class
ऐसी बच्चियों को पढ़ाता हूं। हम लोग क्लास
I do it. This is when I teach identity
में करते हैं। ये मैं जब आइडेंटिटी पढ़ाता
yes, this is the exercise of that paper. And
हूं उस पेपर की एक्सरसाइज है। और
I tell the students that you
विद्यार्थियों से कहता हूं आप अपने
Tell me with your imagination in Vijay Chauhan's
इमेजिनेशन से बताइए विजय चौहान की में
There is deprivation and there are privileges. and in
डेप्रिवेशन है कि प्रिविलेजेस हैं। एंड इन
Most points ahead of Vijay Chauhan
मोस्ट पॉइंट्स विजय चौहान के आगे
Privilege is written there. I say you
प्रिविलेज लिखा होता है। मैं कहता हूं आप
tell me when you compare yourself to me
बताइए कि आप जब मुझसे अपनी तुलना करते हैं
So you can feel that
तो आप इस बात को महसूस कर पा रहे हैं कि
I had so many privileges. You
मेरे पास कितने सारे प्रिविलेजेस थे। आप
How will we fight the battle? if it comes to fighting
कैसे लड़ाई लड़ेंगे? अगर लड़ने की नौबत
will come. Thankfully this is not a fight. I am so
आएगी। थैंकफुली ये लड़ाई नहीं है। मैं तो
I am teaching them. This is an important
सिखा रहा हूं उन्हें। यह एक इंपॉर्टेंट
I always think about this factor. that's why I
फैक्टर मुझे हमेशा से लगता है। इसीलिए मैं
This collective is more important than this individual
इस इंडिविजुअल से ज्यादा इस कलेक्टिव वाली
because he asked for all these deprivations
क्योंकि यह सारे डेप्रिवेशंस उसने मांगे
were not there. Now he has earned these privileges
नहीं थे। उसने अब ये प्रिविलजेस उसने कमाए
weren't there either. met most of the
भी नहीं थे। मिले थे मोस्ट ऑफ द
Privileges because 15-20 year olds
प्रिविलेजेस क्योंकि 15 20 साल के बच्चों
I am talking about. to them which they have
की बात कर रहा हूं। उनको उनके पास जो
Those are privileges given by parents, family
प्रिविलेज है वो पेरेंट्स के दिए, फैमिली
privileges given by the society
के दिए, सोसाइटी के दिए हुए प्रिविलजेस
Are. He did not do anything in that.
हैं। उसमें उन्होंने कुछ नहीं किया था।
Such deprivation is also not their fault.
ऐसे डेप्रिवेशन की भी उनकी गलती नहीं है।
have been given to them. But they had to fight
उनको दिए गए हैं। लेकिन लड़ना उनको पड़ता
Such is the penetration. Stepping Away From Privilege
है ऐसे डेप्रवेश। प्रिविलेज से दूर हटना
It is also the same. what we talked about that judgement
भी वही है। हम जो हमने बात करी कि जजमेंट
move away from. Yes. Right. if you are able to
से दूर हटना। हां। राइट। इफ यू आर एबल टू
Unj You Are Able to Transcend Your Privilege
अनज यू आर एबल टू ट्रांजेंट योर प्रिविलेज
YOU WILL BE ABLE TO SEE THAT THEIR BEHAVIOR IS
यू विल बी एबल टू सी कि उनके व्यवहार के
His absences were working behind him. This much
पीछे उनके अभाव काम कर रहे थे। इतना
There are more value adding podcasts. I don't
ज्यादा वैल्यू एडिंग पडकास्ट है। आई डोंट
No. I mean I am saying what I believe
नो। आई मीन आई एम सेइंग व्हाट आई बिलीव
in.
इन।
All the things I have not learned in the last 10 years
सारी चीजें ना मैंने पिछले 10 सालों में
I have learnt it. we are giving people in a podcast
सीखी है। हम एक पडकास्ट में दे रहे लोगों
To.
को।
The exercise I was mentioning that
जो एक्सरसाइज मैं मेंशन कर रहा था दैट
exercise itself comes from a place of
एक्सरसाइज इटसेल्फ कम्स फ्रॉम अ प्लेस ऑफ़
Privilege. it's no i didn't want to
प्रिविलेज। इट्स नो आई आई डिडंट वांट टू
Say it in these many words. i didn't want
से इट इन दीज़ मेनी वर्ड्स। आई डिडंट वांट
to say in these many words that's why i
टू से इन दीज़ मेनी वर्ड्स दैट्स व्हाई आई
Brother I was being polite here. But this is what
भाई आई वास बीइंग पोलाइट हियर। बट ये जो
When we look at this thing at the individual level
जब हम इंडिविजुअल के लेवल पे इस चीज को
Because that’s what management schools do.
क्योंकि मैनेजमेंट स्कूल यही करते हैं ना।
This is what management schools tell us because
मैनेजमेंट स्कूल यही बताती है क्योंकि
All the kids who have come before him are those who are 20
उनके सामने सारे बच्चे वो आए हैं जो 20
I have come after seeing the fees of Rs one lakh. So to them this
लाख की फीस देखकर आए हैं। तो उनको ये
It seems very easy to teach, look at you
सिखाना बहुत आसान सा लगता है कि देखो आपको
You have to see your strength to get the work done
काम कराने के लिए अपनी स्ट्रेंथ देखनी है
And they need to be sharpened even more. I
और उनको और ज्यादा शार्प करना है। मैं
Sometimes I say that whoever you consider as your strength
कभी-कभी कहता हूं कि जो जिसे आप स्ट्रेंथ
I am saying once on the individual level
कह रहे हैं इंडिविजुअल के लेवल पर एक बार
please put your hand on his heart for a little while
प्लीज थोड़ा सा दिल पे हाथ रख के उसके
Find the source. for example i am
सोर्स को ढूंढ दीजिए। फॉर एग्जांपल आई एम
Doing this exercise. you mentioned about
डूइंग दिस एक्सरसाइज। यू मेंशंड अबाउट
Three things. You said about fitness. Right?
थ्री थिंग्स। यू सेड अबाउट फिटनेस। राइट?
the second thing you mentioned about your
सेकंड थिंग यू मेंशंड अबाउट योर
Communication and the third thing you mentioned.
कम्युनिकेशन एंड थर्ड थिंग यू मेंशंड।
Marketing. Right?
मार्केटिंग। राइट?
just be honest here how much of it is
जस्ट जस्ट बी ऑनेस्ट हियर हाउ मच ऑफ इट इज
actually a product of your private all of
एक्चुअली अ प्रोडक्ट ऑफ योर प्रिविल ऑल ऑफ
it's 100% what i said about myself i mean
इट 100% एस आई सेड अबाउट मसेल्फ आई मीन
there were some deviations in my initial life
देयर वर सम डेबिवेशंस इन माय इनिशियल लाइफ
but most of the time now it is coming out
बट मोस्ट ऑफ़ द टाइम नाउ इट इज़ कमिंग आउट
of privilege so this matter is a little bit
ऑफ़ प्रिविलज़ तो ये जो मामला है ये थोड़ा सा
It also makes us honest and honest towards ourselves
हमें ईमानदार भी बनाता है और अपने प्रति
A little bit shouldn't be too much
थोड़ा थोड़ा सा बहुत ज्यादा नहीं होना चाहिए
But it also makes you a little self critical
लेकिन थोड़ा सा सेल्फ क्रिटिकल भी बनाता है
It also teaches a little self-criticism. Own
थोड़ा सा आत्मलोचन भी सिखाता है। अपनी
A little criticism. like you said no
आलोचना करना थोड़ा सा। जैसे आपने कहा ना
that you distance yourself a little bit
कि थोड़ा सा अपने आप को थोड़ा सा दूर हो
Let's see, friend, the things that I have known till now
के देखना कि यार मैं जिन चीजों को अब तक
I was assuming my earnings, a lot of them
अपनी कमाई मान रहा था उनमें से बहुत सारी
These things were not my earnings. I was given the
चीजें मेरी कमाई थी नहीं। मुझे दी गई थी
Or it fell into my hands. to someone we
या मेरे हाथ लग गई थी। किसी को हम
not even found guilty of privilege
प्रिविलजेस के लिए दोषी भी नहीं ठहरा
Can. trust me i am very very
सकते। ट्रस्ट मी मैं आई एम वेरी वेरी
It is clear to me that I cannot tell anyone now
क्लियर हियर कि ये नहीं कि अब किसी कहें
that brother you are rich and that is why you start
कि भाई तुम अमीर हो और इस कारण यू स्टार्ट
Luthing. no privileges whatsoever is the way
लूथिंग। नो प्रिविलज़ जो हैं वह जिस तरीके
Deprivation from someone by giving application
से डेप्रिवेशन किसी ने एप्लीकेशन देकर
I did not take it. someone has the privilege because
नहीं लिए थे। प्रिविलज़ भी किसी ने इसलिए
They too should not be judged. But if this
उनको भी जज नहीं करना है। लेकिन अगर ये
You have your own privileges then you must work
आपके अपने प्रिविलेज हैं तब आपको जरूर काम
Should be done. I'm just telling them
करना चाहिए। केवल इनको मैं कह रहा हूं
To transcend. Don't even want to leave it.
ट्रांजेंट करने को। छोड़ना भी नहीं है।
Being mindful of your privileges is a
बीइंग माइंडफुल टू योर प्रिविलजेस इज अ
Variant Step in Your Life. Self
वेरीेंट स्टेप इन योर लाइफ। सेल्फ
Awareness. Exactly. Two exercises talk
अवेयरनेस। एक्सक्टली। दो एक्सरसाइज की बात
Curry. To get the strength list out first. Second
करी। पहले स्ट्रेंथ लिस्ट आउट करना। दूसरा
This is Privilege versus Deprivation
ये प्रिविलेज वर्सेस डेप्रिवेशन
Third Exercise: Self Identification
तीसरी एक्सरसाइज सेल्फ आइडेंटिफिकेशन
Factors behind societal self
फैक्टर्स बिय्ड सोसाइटल सेल्फ
Identification. Ok? Because the one who
आइडेंटिफिकेशन। ठीक है? क्योंकि वो जो
Exercise of Privilege Versus Deprivation
प्रिविलेज वर्सेस डेप्रिवेशन की एक्सरसाइज
Yes, they are all social. Right now this is mine
है वो सारे सोसाइटल है। अभी ये जो मेरी
The third list is this is from the perspective
थर्ड लिस्ट है दिस इज़ फ्रॉम द पर्सपेक्टिव
Of self improvement. Ok? then i would
ऑफ़ सेल्फ इंप्रूवमेंट। ठीक है? तो आई वुड
To divide it into two parts. may be the
से कि डिवाइड इट इंटू टू पार्ट्स। मे बी द
The first five are areas you can improve.
फर्स्ट फाइव इज़ एरियाज यू कैन इंप्रूव।
No what else can I do? what are
नहीं मैं और क्या कर सकता हूं? व्हाट आर
My actual weaknesses? This is very important
माय एक्चुअल वीकनेसेस? ये बहुत जरूरी है
At this stage.
एट दिस स्टेज।
and the next five probably I don't know
एंड द नेक्स्ट फाइव प्रोबब्ली आई डोंट नो
More Self-Identification Factors That You Can Know
मोर सेल्फ आइडेंटिफिकेशन फैक्टर्स कि आप
From what perspective do you view the world? own
दुनिया को किस नजरिए से देखते हो। खुद की
From what perspective do you look at life? Where
जिंदगी को किस नजरिए से देखते हो। कहां
Do you want to go? you know dreams dreams
जाना चाह रहे हो? यू नो ड्रीम्स ड्रीम्स
and aspirations if all these things are yours
एंड एस्पिरेशंस अगर ये सारी चीजें आपके
Are in front. It's a very strong mirror too
सामने हैं। इट्स अ वेरी स्ट्रांग मिरर टू
Work from. Assuming that you are executing
वर्क फ्रॉम। अस्यूमिंग कि आप एग्जीक्यूशन
You are doing it, you are working hard etc.
कर रहे हो, हार्ड वर्क कर रहे हो वगैरह।
But Sir, I would like to ask you this now, please accept
पर सर मैं यह पूछना चाहूंगा अब कि मान लो
If there is a person who has that privilege
अगर कोई ऐसा इंसान है जिसने वो प्रिविलेज
Versus deprivation everywhere on the chart
वर्सेस डेप्रिवेशन चार्ट में हर जगह
Deprivation or deprivation in many places
डेप्रिवेशन या बहुत सारी जगह डेप्रिवेशन
Six out of 10 deprivation points or
सिक्स आउट ऑफ 10 डेप्रिवेशन पॉइंट्स या
Even five out of 10 that person is third
इवन फाइव आउट ऑफ़ 10 वो इंसान इस थर्ड
How to Approach the List of My Weaknesses
लिस्ट को कैसे अप्रोच करेगा माय वीकनेसेस
and dreams and aspirations
एंड ड्रीम्स एंड एस्पिरेशंस
you rightly point out a predicament here
यू राइटली पॉइंट आउट अ प्रेडिकमेंट हियर
There is a kind of irony here, an RNA
यहां पर एक किस्म की विडंबना है एक आरएनए
Which needs to be understood. Yes. This exercise which
जिसे समझना पड़े। जी। ये एक्सरसाइज जो
I have told you many times that this exercise is also for you
मैंने कही थी कई बार ये एक्सरसाइज भी अपने
Exercises that come out of your privileges
आप के प्रिविलेजेस से निकली हुई एक्सरसाइज
that if you assume that you have this
है कि अगर आप मान लीजिए आपके पास आपने ये
I made a list of eight, nine or ten of them.
लिस्ट बनाई उसमें से आठ नौ या 10 के 10
If the privilege comes out then you are already on the elephant
प्रिविलेज निकले तो आप पहले ही हाथी पे
Went and boarded it. You are all over the world
जाके सवार हो गए। आप तो सारी दुनिया में
It has been happening. But like you said, there is no
रही है। लेकिन जैसा आपने कहा कि कोई ऐसा
The person is mostly depressed. They
व्यक्ति जिसमें अधिकतर डेप्रिवेश है। वो
How did you nurture your dreams? how does he fulfil his dreams
कैसे सपने पाले? वो कैसे सपनों को पूरा
try to do. So I have used this
करने की कोशिश करें। इसलिए मैंने इस
Talked about overcoming depreciation. You
ओवरकमिंग दी डेप्रबिएशन की बात की थी। आप
Society cannot be changed immediately. an ideal society
तुरंत समाज नहीं बदल सकते। एक आदर्श समाज
In an ideal society such a situation does not arise
में एक आइडियल सोसाइटी में ऐसी नौबत नहीं
Should have come. but our society
आनी चाहिए थी। लेकिनकि हमारी सोसाइटी
also reproduces deprivations and
डेप्रिवेशंस का भी रिप्रोडक्शन करती है और
It also reproduces privileges.
प्रिविलेजेस का भी रिप्रोडक्शन करती है।
It is very easy to understand. Did you understand it?
इट इज़ वेरी ईजी टू अंडरस्टैंड। समझे ना?
Let's say your parents are very wealthy.
कि मान लीजिए आपके माता-पिता बहुत संपन्न
There were persons. What to do? to our own child
व्यक्ति थे। क्या करेंगे? अपने बच्चे को
Will put you in school. This is their job, brother.
स्कूल में डालेंगे। यह उनका काम है भाई।
What happened to being a parent?
माता-पिता होने के नाते क्या हुआ?
Privileges reproduce privileges
प्रिविलजेस ने प्रिविलजेस को रिप्रोड्यूस
Did. Same reproductiveism as deprivation
किया। सेम यही प्रजननवाद डेप्रिवेशन के
It goes together as well. They are poor parents. Poor thing
साथ भी चलता है। गरीब मां-बाप हैं। बेचारे
If you cannot send them to school or if you do
स्कूल भेज ही नहीं पाएंगे या भेजेंगे तो
will send him to some poor school where he
किसी गरीब स्कूल में भेजेंगे जहां पे वो
And he might be learning less. Hence the major point
और कम सीख रहा होगा। इसलिए द मेजर पॉइंट
There are two things. Forest
इज टू थिंग्स। वन
Because this is not an ideal society. Ideal
इज़ आदर्श समाज ये क्योंकि नहीं है। आदर्श
If there was a society then the poor child would also be in the same school
समाज होता तो गरीब बच्चा भी उसी स्कूल में
The school where a rich man's child would be going
जा रहा होता जिस स्कूल में अमीर का बच्चा
I would have been going. So despite this poverty
जा रहा होता। तो यह गरीबी होने के बावजूद
The impact of deprivation would be less because
डेप्रिवेशन का इंपैक्ट कम होता क्योंकि
Reproduction would have been less but we are not
रिप्रोडक्शन कम होता लेकिन वी आर नॉट
Living in an Ideal Society. So a society like this
लिविंग इन एन आइडियल सोसाइटी। तो ऐसे समाज
in whichever you are, the child coming from depression
में जो जो आप डेप्रिवेशन से आ रहे बच्चे
are they or are they for them these deprivations
हैं या वो हैं उनके लिए इन डेप्रिवेशंस को
a way to overcome
ओवरकम करने की एक
So you need to start exercising.
तो एक्सरसाइज शुरू करने की जरूरत है।
But secondly you also have to understand that
लेकिन दूसरा आपको यह भी समझना है कि फिर
You don't have to have the exact same dreams
आपको ठीक वही सपने लेने की मजबूरी नहीं है
The compulsion you have with that person
आपके पास जो मजबूरी उस व्यक्ति के पास है
Who has constant privileges. this to this
जिसके पास लगातार प्रिविलेजेस है। इस इसको
The way I say it is,
मैं जिस तरीके से कहता हूं वो यह है कि
Please do a reality check. Ouch. Ok?
प्लीज एक रियलिटी चेक कीजिए। उफ। ठीक है?
and try and start working on a
एंड ट्राई एंड स्टार्ट वर्किंग ऑन अ
The Incremental Thing. Ok? my language
इंकमेंटल थिंग। ठीक है? मेरी वाली भाषा
If I talk about it then I would say straight IAS
में बात करें तो मैं कहता हूं सीधा आईएएस
Don't think of becoming one. Then if you have it
बनने की मत सोचो। फिर अगर आपके पास यह
It is not that you can tolerate five failures
नहीं है कि आप पांच फेलियर बर्दाश्त कर
Can be done. Assume four failure tolerance
सकते हैं। चार फेलियर बर्दाश मान लीजिए
You have to be there in the sixth attempt. Your
सिक्स्थ अटेम्प्ट में आपका होना है। आपके
You have the right to tolerate five failures
आपको पांच फेलियर बर्दाश्त करने का आपके
There must be an ecosystem nearby. a thriving place
पास इकोसिस्टम होना चाहिए। एक संपन्न जगह
The person coming from Five Failures
से आने वाला व्यक्ति पांच फेलियर्स
can tolerate it. Five startups
बर्दाश्त कर सकता है। पांच स्टार्टअप
Can tolerate failure. five second
फेलियर बर्दाश्त कर सकता है। पांच दूसरे
Can tolerate failure. but you
फेलियर बर्दाश्त कर सकता है। लेकिन आप
Can't do it. So what do you do? you again
नहीं कर सकते। तो आप क्या करें? आप फिर
Do it incrementally. let's start with the
इंक्रीमेंटल करिए। लेट्स स्टार्ट विद द
SSC Preparation. Ok? now this is
एसएससी प्रिपरेशन। ठीक है? अब दिस इज़
What I am saying is wrong. in a sense that
व्हाट आई एम सेइंग इज़ रोंग। इन अ सेंस कि
In an ideal society such a situation should not arise
एक आइडियल समाज में ऐसा नहीं नौबत आनी
A motivational speaker should have said this
चाहिए थी कि कोई मोटिवेशनल स्पीकर यह कहे
That you should dream small. I am saying that the
कि छोटे सपने लो। मैं ये कह रहा हूं कि जो
People are saying always dream big. that
लोग कह रहे हैं कि हमेशा बड़े सपने लो। दैट
is coming from certain privileges. You
इज कमिंग फ्रॉम सर्टेन प्रिविलेजेस। आप
Start with your reality check. first thing
अपना रियलिटी चेक से शुरू कीजिए। पहली चीज
because any dream can happen to individuals
इंडिविजुअल्स को क्योंकि कोई भी सपने आई
Have written whole papers on this. dreams and
हैव रिटन होल पेपर्स ऑन दिस। सपने और
Aspirations are constructs
एस्पिरेशंस जो होते हैं वो कंस्ट्रक्ट्स
There are. They are not objective. so
होते हैं। ऑब्जेक्टिव नहीं होते। इसलिए
The whole country has the same dreams
पूरा देश एक ही जैसे सपने
But this is a scary thing. first of all you
ले ये डरावनी बात है। आप सबको पहले तो
Made them stand at different places. Then all of the
अलग-अलग जगह पे खड़ा कर दिया। फिर सारे के
Take all the different dreams of the same person. That means that
सारे अलग-अलग एक ही सपना लीजिए। यानी कि
Everyone's starting point is different. or else
सबका स्टार्टिंग पॉइंट अलग-अलग है। या फिर
I told you that this is everyone's target. Who
कह दिया कि यही सबका टारगेट है। कौन
Everybody knows he will win. I am one of life
जीतेगा सबको पता है। मैं जिंदगी के एक
I would like to talk about the truth sir.
सत्य के बारे में बात करना चाहूंगा सर।
Please do what Virat does for us in cricket
प्लीज डू जो हमारे लिए क्रिकेट में विराट
It is Kohli. HARD WORK,
कोहली है। हार्ड वर्क,
Success,
सक्सेस,
A LOT OF IMPROVEMENT A COBI BRAND
इंप्रूवमेंट अ कोबी ब्रांड का एक बहुत
There is a famous Nike ad which is actually their
मशहूर नाइकी ऐड है जो एक्चुअली उनकी
It is based on mentality.
मेंटालिटी पे बेस्ड है।
That’s basically what he’s saying there. and their
वहां वो बेसिकली ये कह रहे हैं। और उनकी
Mentality is not known all over the world
मेंटालिटी ना पूरी दुनिया में जानी जाती
This is age Mamba mentality. because their
है एज मांबा मेंटालिटी। क्योंकि उनका
The nickname was Black Mamba which was the name of a snake
निकनेम था ब्लैक मांबा जो एक सांप का नाम
It happens. Right? because when you see them
होता है। राइट? क्योंकि जब आप उनके
You will watch those basketball clips, right?
बास्केटबॉल के क्लिप्स देखोगे ना वो
Plays exactly like an aggressive snake.
बिल्कुल अग्रेसिव सांप की तरह खेलते हैं।
Play with a lot of concentration and dedication.
बहुत दिमाग लगाकर लगन के साथ खेलते हैं।
And he was famous for his training regime.
एंड ही वास फेमस फॉर ह ट्रेनिंग रिजीम।
That means the discipline was of a very high level
यानी कि डिसिप्लिन बहुत हाई लेवल का था
their. But the logic of his life was basic.
उनका। बट उनके लाइफ का लॉजिक बेसिक ही था।
That friend, you don't need to become a parent
कि यार आपको ना मां-बाप बनने की जरूरत
Not there. All you need is Betterment.
नहीं है। आपको बस बेटरमेंट की जरूरत है।
That was a simple message from Nikki. don't worry
वो Nikki की सिंपल मैसेज थी। डोंट वरी
About the long term. just try getting
अबाउट द लॉन्ग टर्म। जस्ट ट्राई गेटिंग
Better Everyday. Just get better. That's all. I
बेटर एवरीडे। जस्ट गेट बेटर। दैट्स ऑल। आई
I think this is somewhere, especially me
थिंक ये ना कहीं ना कहीं एस्पेशली मेरे
I am looking around in my age group
आसपास मैं देख रहा हूं मेरे ऐज ग्रुप में
Many people are forgetting this. to Betterment
बहुत लोग ये भूल रहे हैं। बेटरमेंट को
leave it it's easier to get better through your
छोड़ इट्स इट्स इजी टू गेट बेटर थ्रू योर
20h. I don't drive that much after 30 years
20ज। हम 30ज के बाद ना वो वो ड्राइव
In many cases, they get removed. come in many
बहुतों में हट जाते हैं। बहुतों में आ भी
Let's go. See this also, two groups are being formed.
जाते हैं। ये भी देख दो ग्रुप बन रहे हैं।
The one who is chasing Betterment. Others
एक जो बेटरमेंट को चस कर रहे हैं। दूसरे
Those who left Betterment with a little
जिन्होंने बेटरमेंट को थोड़ा सा छोड़ दिया
Is. This is what I observe. a butt please
है। दिस इज व्हाट आई ऑब्जर्व। अ बट प्लीज
Correct me if I am wrong. so i feel that
करेक्ट मी इफ आई एम रोंग। सो आई फील कि
Even if you don't have privilege in your life
अगर आपकी जिंदगी में प्रिविलेज है भी नहीं
Even then this logic will apply. Exactly
तो भी यह लॉजिक तो अप्लाई होगा। एक्सक्टली
it is a matter of getting better somewhere
इट इज हल्के से कहीं ना कहीं बेटर होने की
try that's what i said overcoming the
कोशिश दैट्स व्हाट आई सेड ओवरकमिंग द
This is what devolution of privileges means
प्रिविलेजेस का डेबिवेशन का मतलब ही ये है
that and that's why i am saying be a better
कि एंड दैट्स व्हाई आई एम सेइंग बी अ बेटर
Person Than You Were Yesterday. Lived this many times.
पर्सन देन यू वर यस्टरडे। इतना बार जी।
IATA change is 1% change. Suppose you are racing
आईटा चेंज 1% का चेंज। मान लीजिए आप रेस
Reached the track and another one with you
ट्रैक पर पहुंचे और आपके साथ में एक दूसरा
The person is standing. You said I will do this
व्यक्ति खड़ा है। आप कहा मैं तो इसको इससे
I will leave it behind to run. It is possible
इसके पीछे छोडूंगा दौड़ लगाने। हो सकता है
He's an Olympian. Is it okay? It is possible
वो ओलंपियन हो। ठीक है ना? हो सकता है
He might have given that thing 15 years ago.
उसने 15 साल पहले दे दिया हो उस चीज को।
Maybe he has some other privilege.
हो सकता है उसके पास दूसरा प्रिविलेज हो।
Don't compare yourself with that person.
डोंट कंपेयर योरसेल्फ विद दैट पर्सन।
Compare yourself with you of yesterday.
कंपेयर योरसेल्फ ऑफ विद यू ऑफ यस्टरडे।
If you work for this much then you are disrespectful
अगर आप इतने पे काम करते हैं तो डिस्पाइट
Your deprivations. You will be able to overcome
योर डेप्रिवेशंस। यू विल बी एबल टू ओवरकम
Many many aspects of your depression.
मेनी मेनी आस्पेक्ट्स ऑफ योर डेप्रिवेश।
Brother, when I look at myself, I
भाई मैं अपने आप को जब देखता हूं तो मैं
I see that yes I did and I am nothing
देखता हूं कि हां मैंने और मैं कुछ नहीं
I can do it. I cannot claim that
कर सकता। मैं ऐसा दावा नहीं कर सकता कि
I am the best teacher in the world. Country
मैं दुनिया का सबसे अच्छा शिक्षक हूं। देश
I am the best teacher. I claim this
का सबसे अच्छा शिक्षक हूं। मैं ये दावा
can't. I just more and more
नहीं कर सकता। मैं सिर्फ ज्यादा से ज्यादा
I can claim that last semester
यह दावा कर सकता हूं कि पिछले सेमेस्टर
Like I taught it. I am trying to
में मैंने जैसे पढ़ाया था। मैं कोशिश कर
I can hope that I can meet him this semester
सकता हूं कि इस सेमेस्टर में मैं उससे
I will teach better. Vijendra as a human being
बेहतर पढ़ाऊंगा। इंसान के तौर पर विजेंद्र
Chauhan comes out of the poverty that he faced
चौहान अपने जिन अभावों के से निकल कर आता
Is. Vijendra Chauhan, a poor slum in Delhi
है। विजेंद्र चौहान दिल्ली की गरीब बस्ती
It comes out from. On that basis I
से निकल कर आता है। उसके बेसिस पे मैंने
I have travelled something. i may not be on
आई हैव ट्रेवल्ड समथिंग। आई मे नॉट बी ऑन
The Top of the World. Is it okay? I may not
द टॉप ऑफ द वर्ल्ड। ठीक है ना? आई मे नॉट
B and I don't intend to. But I have read that
बी एंड आई डोंट इंटेंड टू। लेकिन मैंने उस
I have done the journey. journey is
जर्नी को किया है। जर्नी इज
Morant Then
मोरेंट देन
Destination. There is another career factor.
डेस्टिनेशन। एक और करियर फैक्टर होता है।
And I would love for you to break this down
एंड आई वुड लव फॉर यू टू ब्रेक डाउन दिस
Career factor and what ever. and disagree
करियर फैक्टर एंड व्हाटएवर। और डिसएग्री
with me. I call this factor ethical
विथ मी। इस फैक्टर को मैं कहता हूं एथिकल
Messy behavior. Right? I will answer you. this people
कमीनापन। राइट? आई आंसर दे। इसे लोग
Also called street smarts.
स्ट्रीट स्मार्ट्स भी कहते हैं।
Don't hurt anyone's feelings, or anyone's career
अ किसी का दिल ना दुखाना, किसी के करियर
Do not hurt anyone in life
को चोट ना पहुंचाना, किसी की जिंदगी में
Don’t bring a pen. Yet a little bit of bastardry is alive
पेन ना लाना। येट थोड़ा सा कमीनापन जिंदा
Keep it for your own protection. End
रखना खुद के प्रोटेक्शन के लिए। एंड
A To move forward faster. Self
अ ज्यादा तेजी से आगे बढ़ने के लिए। खुद
To accelerate the career of. See if this
के करियर की तेजी के लिए। देखिए अगर यह
If it is in your control then I don't think so
आपके आपके बस में है तो मुझे नहीं लगता कि
Is there any problem in this? I am from an example
इसमें कोई परेशानी है। मैं एक एग्जांपल से
If I tell you, maybe you will understand better
बताऊंगा तो शायद और बेहतर तरीके से समझ
I will come. You will now find out that
में आएगा। आपको अभी पता लग गया होगा कि
About my privileges and deprivations
मेरे प्रिविलेजेस और डेप्रिवेशन को लेके
What are my principles? On that basis I
मेरे क्या सिद्धांत है। उसके बेसिस पे मैं
I often say one thing. I say that
एक बात अक्सर बोलता हूं। मैं कहता हूं कि
If and when you understand the reference to this
अगर और ये आप इसका रेफरेंस समझ पाएंगे तो
You will understand. I say that if you
समझ में आएगा। मैं कहता हूं कि अगर आप
of Uttar Pradesh, of Bihar, of Rajasthan
उत्तर प्रदेश के, बिहार के, राजस्थान के
Which is called Hindi region. many people
हिंदी प्रदेश जिसे कहा जाता है। कई लोग
This is called cow belt, cow dung strip
इसे काऊ बेल्ट कहते हैं, गोबर पट्टी कहते
Are. Many call it Hindi speaking states. whichever you
हैं। कई हिंदी प्रदेश कहते हैं। जो भी आप
Call it right. here are the boys coming from
इसको सही कहें। यहां से आ रहे लड़के हैं
So I say that you should study hard to become an IAS.
तो मैं कहता हूं कि आपको आईएएस बनने के
If it comes to your mind then
बारे में अगर आपके मन में आया है तो उसको
Should be rejected. think again
खारिज कर देना चाहिए। दोबारा से सोचना
Needed has it come again or not
चाहिए। दोबारा भी आ गया है कि नहीं नहीं
Even if I want to become one, please reject me.
मुझे तो बनना है तब भी खारिज कर दीजिए।
Think about it for the third time. survives even after three times
तीसरी बार सोचिए। तीन बार के बाद भी बचता
If it is there then become it. and here comes the second thing
है तो बनिए। और यहां पर वो दूसरी बात आएगी
Which is about you. but if you are in this area
जो आपके बारे में। लेकिन अगर आप इस इलाके
She is a girl from and not in your mind
से आई हुई लड़की हैं और आपके मन में नहीं
I also want to become an IAS. but you have to leave home
भी है कि आईएएस बनना है। लेकिन आपको घर से
It is proposed that son Delhi
यह प्रस्ताव दिया जाता है कि बेटा दिल्ली
Go and get ready. Grab it quickly.
जाओ तैयारी कर लो। झट से झपट के ले लीजिए।
Now you can see that this makes sense
अब अब आप देख सकते हैं कि इसमें एक सेंस
I have the smartness that I'm saying
में वो वाली चतुरता है जो मैं कह रहा हूं
if you are a boy then I am saying that
कि अगर आप लड़के हैं तो मैं कह रहा हूं कि
This isn't yours at all. Someone else gave me the dream
यह आपका है ही नहीं। सपना किसी और ने दे
has given it. You are being sent forcibly.
दिया है। आपको जबरदस्ती भेजा जा रहा है।
The family members need God. family members
घर वाले घर वालों को रब चाहिए। घर वालों
needs money. money as dowry to the family
को पैसा चाहिए। घर वालों को दहेज में पैसा
Needed The family members felt a kind of
चाहिए। घर वालों को एक तरह का उधर उस
The word going around in the area is 'we want Bhaukaal'.
इलाके में शब्द चलता है भौकाल चाहिए।
That's why I am asking you to become an IAS.
इसलिए आपको आईएएस बनने के लिए कह रहे हैं।
But if you are a girl and you have to face even more liars
लेकिन अगर आप लड़की हो और आपको झूठे से भी
It is said that go son and prepare yourself
कहा जाता है कि जा बेटा तैयारी कर ले तो
Grab it immediately and that one next
तुरंत झपट के ले लीजिए और आगे वो वाली
The smart thing is coming and the ethical thing is going
चातुर्य वाली बात आ रही है और एथिकल जाकर
It is a matter of cleverness. I say this
चातुर्य वाली बात है। मैं ये कहता हूं
Why? So if you go to Delhi
क्यों? इसलिए कि अगर आप दिल्ली जाकर
they prepare and after 2 years of preparation
तैयारी करती हैं और 2 साल तैयारी के बाद
You would not have been selected. even then in this 2 years
आपका नहीं होता सिलेक्शन। तब भी इस 2 साल
Living in a big city, away from the confines of home
में बड़े शहर में रहना, घर के बंधनों से
Staying away, freedom, it teaches you so much
दूर रहना, फ्रीडम यह आपको इतना कुछ सिखा
which otherwise you will not be able to learn. Now
जाएगी जो अदरवाइज आप नहीं सीख पाएंगे। अब
This is a kind of cleverness. with family members
ये एक तरह की चालाकी है। घर वालों के साथ
There is definitely some dishonesty involved as well.
निश्चित तौर पे एक तरह की बेईमानी भी है।
Is it okay? Dishonesty in the sense that the family
ठीक है ना? बेईमानी इन द सेंस कि घर वाले
They are saying that become an IAS. You know
कह रहे हैं कि आईएएस बन जाओ। आपको पता है
That you don’t even have to become. you also want
कि आपको बनना भी नहीं है। आप चाहते भी
Not there. Maybe you have that thing inside you
नहीं है। आपका शायद आपके अंदर वो उस उस
There is no caliber of variety either. But you
किस्म का कैलिबर भी नहीं है। लेकिन आपको
I know that this path is giving
ये पता है कि ये जो पाथ है इट इज़ गिविंग
you some taste of freedom which otherwise is
यू सम टेस्ट ऑफ़ फ्रीडम व्हिच अदरवाइज इज़
not available to girls of this particular
नॉट अवेलेबल टू गर्ल्स ऑफ़ दिस पर्टिकुलर
Reese. So what happened to one kind of thing? exactly
रीज़। तो एक तरह का क्या हुआ? एक्जेक्टली
Same is applicable on other things. If this
सेम इज़ एप्लीकेबल ऑन अदर थिंग्स। इफ यह
cleverness to bypass those deprivations
चालाकीपन उन डेप्रिवेशंस को बायपास करने
Comes with tools of. We, including you, have no
के टूल्स लेकर आता है। हम जिनमें आपका कोई
There was no role. Your Society Provided to You
रोल नहीं था। आपको प्रदत्त आपकी सोसाइटी
gave you, were social and gave you a little
ने आपको दिए थे, सोशल थे और आपको थोड़ी सी
You are able to cleverly bypass it.
चालाकी से आप इसे बाईपास कर पा रहे हैं।
I don't see any arm in it. so would you
आई डोंट सी एनी आर्म इन इट। सो वुड यू
also that the more the privilege the more
आल्सो से कि जितना ज्यादा प्रिविलेज उतनी
More cleverness on the contrary what I am
ज्यादा चालाकी ऑन द कंट्रा व्हाट आई एम
Saying so awesome. I'm saying if you are
सेइंग सो ऑोजिट। आई एम सेइंग इफ यू आर
Coming from deprivation then some cleverness is
कमिंग फ्रॉम डेप्रिवेशन देन सम चालाकी इज
It is forgiveable.
इज़ फॉरगिवेबल।
Ok? If you are coming from deprivation.
ठीक है? इफ यू आर कमिंग फ्रॉम डेप्रिवेशन।
If you are coming from privileged
इफ यू आर कमिंग फ्रॉम प्रिविलेजेस जो
Otherwise you will find meanness in your language
अदरवाइज ही आपको आपकी भाषा में कमीनापन
Teaches. Is it okay? and you his and
सिखाता है। ठीक है ना? और आप उसका और
If you are using it more then it is like
ज्यादा इस्तेमाल कर रहे हैं तो इट्स लाइक
you are already on a horse and you have the most
यू आर ऑलरेडी ऑन अ हॉर्स और आपको सबसे
That sharp sword was also given. you will
शार्प जो है वो तलवार भी दे दी गई। यू विल
End up killing people work deprecated. We
एंड अप किलिंग पीपल वर्क डिप्रेक्ट। हम
If you already assume that it means Mumbai
अगर आप पहले से ही मान लीजिए मतलब मुंबई
I am saying this because I am sitting here. let's assume
में बैठे हैं इसलिए कह रहे हैं। मान लीजिए
You come from a star family. Struggle
आप एक स्टार फैमिली से आते हैं। स्ट्रगल
I am doing this to enter Bollywood. Correct
कर रहे हैं बॉलीवुड में जाने के लिए। ठीक
Isn't it? Already comes from a star family.
है ना? पहले से स्टार फैमिली से आते हैं।
All the directors know. to dad
सारे डायरेक्टर जानते हैं। पिताजी को
The producers know. Is it okay? and such
प्रोड्यूसर जानते हैं। ठीक है ना? और ऐसे
I mean something else which you are calling cleverness
में आप कोई और मतलब जिसे आप चालाकी कह रहे
They were also trying to suppress these four people
थे वो भी करने लगे हैं चार लोगों को दबाने
For. That's unfair to some extent. But
के लिए। दैट्स अनफेयर टू सम एक्सटेंट। पर
This is also the truth of the world. Exactly this
ये दुनिया का सच भी है। एक्सैक्टली ये
It also happens. in fact these are the privileges
होता भी है। इनफैक्ट ये ये जो प्रिविलेजेस
You have this cleverness and more
है वो आपको ये वाली चालाकी और ज्यादा
I teach because these privileges have
सिखाते हैं क्योंकि इन इन प्रिविलेजेस ने
It is seen that to survive and to thrive.
यह देखा है कि टू सर्वाइव एंड टू थ्राइव।
If you have these things inside you, then you
आपके अंदर यह वाली चीजें अगर होंगी तो यू
will do better because a big fight will follow
विल डू बेटर क्योंकि एक बड़ी लड़ाई तो
In fact, Joe
दरअसल जो जो
There are rightful contenders to suppress them
राइटफुल कंटेंडर्स हैं उन्हें दबाने की
fight with. Sir, I know the feeling of meanness
लड़ाई है। सर पता है आई फील कि कमीनापन की
There is a place and there is also a degree. Yes
भी जगह होती है और डिग्री भी होती है। हां
There is also a degree. more or less but one of his
डिग्री भी होती है। कम ज्यादा पर उसकी एक
There should be a limit. Exactly and for me
लिमिट होनी चाहिए। एक्जेक्टली और मेरे लिए
And I know we probably disagree a little
एंड आई नो वी प्रोबब्ली डिसएग्री लिटिल
Bit on this but for me that bastard I
बिट ऑन दिस पर मेरे लिए वो कमीनापन मैं
I limit my likes because of God
लिमिट करता हूं अ ऊपर वाले की वजह से लाइक
I always think in my mind that
मेरे दिमाग में मैं हमेशा ये सोचता हूं कि
God is watching everything and he is thinking
भगवान सब कुछ देख रहे हैं और वो सोचते हुए
Let's live our life, no one cares about it
जिंदगी जी चलिए मतलब कोई भी इस पर तो
Welcome to Ristron wherever it comes from. Ok
रिस्ट्रन जहां से आए स्वागत है। ठीक है
No? but I mean you know I
ना? लेकिन मतलब मैं आप जानते हैं कि मैं
I am relatively an atheist person. so I
रिलेटिवली एक एथस्ट व्यक्ति हूं। तो मैं
I don't leave it at that thing. But
इसको इसको उस चीज पर नहीं छोड़ता। लेकिन
Certainly, I take it for granted that
इतना जरूर है कि मैं ये मानकर चलता हूं कि
Being ethical is the responsibility of being a human being.
एथिकल होना मनुष्य होने की जिम्मेदारी है।
But how do you bring in this limitingness again?
बट ये लिमिटिंगनेस आप फिर कैसे लाते हो?
Look, you can think of it this way, maybe
देखिए आप इसको इस तरीके से समझिए कि शायद
This is the age difference. atheism which
ये उम्र के वाले अंतर है। एथिस्म जो चीज
not believing in god is
होती है ईश्वर में विश्वास ना करना जो
This is the stage after believing
होता है यह विश्वास करने के बाद का स्टेज
Is. There is no stage before this. you understand
है। इससे पहले का स्टेज नहीं है। आप समझ
Are you getting it? This is after that, all of us, all of us
पा रहे हैं? ये उसके बाद का हम सब हम सब
People's families would just make a theist and move on
लोगों के परिवार थीस्ट तो बना के ही चलते
Isn't it? when you transcend it
हैं ना। आप जब इसको ट्रांसेंट करते हैं जब
say no maybe now I'm at that level
कहते हैं कि नहीं अब शायद मैं उस स्तर पर
I have reached the point where I can be moral
पहुंच चुका हूं जहां नैतिक होने के लिए
I don't need the extra curbs.
मुझे अतिरिक्त अंकुश की जरूरत नहीं है।
I accept my responsibility to
मैं अपनी जिम्मेदारी मानता हूं कि मैं
I will remain ethical. Brother where did you come from ultimately
नैतिक रहूंगा। भाई अल्टीमेटली कहां से आया
These? This is the success of faith in God
ये? ये जो ईश्वर पर विश्वास का सफल का
Where does the whole philosophy come from? It comes from this
पूरा फलसफा आता कहां से? ये इस बात से आता
When a human is born, he has to do some work
है कि मनुष्य जब पैदा हुआ तो कुछ काम
Some good deeds are bad. You had to give this sense, right?
अच्छे कुछ काम बुरे। ये सेंस देनी थी ना
Anyone. Earlier there was no state. after
किसी को। पहले तो स्टेट भी नहीं था। बाद
When I came to the state, it was decided that this
में तो स्टेट आ गया तो तय हो गया कि यह
It is a crime, it is not a crime. So the law is
अपराध है यह अपराध नहीं है। तो कानून यह
I started thinking that if you do any such work
काम करने लगा कि आप अगर ऐसा कोई भी काम
if you do something that is not good for the society
करते हैं जो समाज के लिए अच्छा नहीं है तो
You can be sent to jail. to you and others
आपको जेल भेज सकते हैं। आपको और दूसरे
crime criminal wala which is justice delivery
अपराध अपराधी वाला जो जस्टिस डिलीवरी है
They can do it. Earlier even this was not there.
वो कर सकते हैं। पहले तो यह भी नहीं था।
So why would anyone do this? It was said that
तो क्यों कौन करेगा यह? यह कहा गया कि
No, you are doing anything. There's somebody who sees
नहीं आप कुछ भी कर रहे हो। कोई है जो देख
Used to be. Is it okay? So you are in awe of this someone
रहा है। ठीक है ना? तो आप इस कोई है के भय
I was doing ethical work. become moral
में एथिकल काम कर रहे थे। नैतिक हो जाते
because you were afraid that otherwise
थे क्योंकि आपको यह डर था कि नहीं तो
In the Past After Life
पास्ट आफ्टर लाइफ में
You will have to go to hell. you have another
आपको नर्क में जाना पड़ेगा। आपको दूसरी
Had to do something. but once you as a human
चीज करनी पड़ी। बट वंस यू एज अ ह्यूमन
Being
बीइंग
Realize once you realize that
रियलाइज आपने एक बार यह महसूस कर लिया कि
no not because someone is watching you
नहीं आपकी कोई देख रहा है इसलिए नहीं
Being moral is the essence of being human
नैतिक होना आपके मनुष्य होने की
There is responsibility. Once you feel this inside you
जिम्मेदारी है। ये एक बार एहसास आपके अंदर
If it comes, you will get the whip of this extra control
आ गया तो आपको इस अतिरिक्त अंकुश की चाबुक
the need will be reduced. It will end. One
की जरूरत कम हो जाएगी। खत्म हो जाएगी। एक
Once this time comes you don't have to fear it
बार जैसे यह आ गया तो आपके पास यह डर नहीं
is it not because I will die for it
है कि इसलिए नहीं कि मैं मर जाऊंगा उसके
Afterwards I will get heaven or hell. So that
बाद मुझे स्वर्ग या नर्क मिलेगा। इसलिए कि
To be moral in this life is to be human
इसी जिंदगी में भी नैतिक होना मनुष्य होने
Because it is my responsibility. This one time
के कारण मेरी जिम्मेदारी है। ये एक बार
If you realize then you will get this extra
एहसास हो गया तो फिर आपको इस अतिरिक्त
There will be no need for controls. So this is his
अंकुश की जरूरत नहीं रह जाएगी। तो ये उसके
It is a later stage. there is no earlier stage
बाद की स्टेज है। पहले की स्टेज नहीं है
that you because you want to mess everything up
कि आप क्योंकि आप सब गड़बड़ करना चाहते
That is why you don't believe in God.
हैं इसलिए आप ईश्वर यकीन नहीं करते हैं।
But also only 1% people are able to do this. Very
बट आल्सो ये वन% लोग कर पाते हैं। बहुत
It's going to be difficult but mind it
इट्स गोइंग टू बी डिफिकल्ट लेकिन माइंड इट
This thing is going on a lot these days. so
यह बात तो आजकल खूब चल भी रही है। इसलिए
You may have noticed that those who believe
कोई आपने देखा होगा कि जो लोग यकीन करते
There are also people like you, I am not talking about them. You
भी हैं आप जैसों की बात नहीं कर रहा। आपने
So a little bit of spirituality
तो थोड़ा सा एक स्पिरिचुअलिटी की एक
Philosophy must have been created. But most people
फिलॉसफी पैदा की होगी। लेकिन अधिकांश लोग
only for your god only for your god
केवल अपने भगवान के लिए अपने ईश्वर के लिए
Believe. If the rest of the 400 religions are accepted then
विश्वास करते हैं। बाकी अगर 400 धर्म मान
If taken for 399 then that too is no confidence
लिए जाए तो 399 के लिए तो वो भी अविश्वास
I do the same. even if you are a very great
ही करते हैं। इवन इफ यू आर अ वेरी ग्रेट
Devout Believer You Are Believer Only 255%
डिवाउट बिलीवर यू आर बिलीवर ओनली 255%
Because for the rest of the believers you are
क्योंकि फॉर रेस्ट ऑफ द बिलीव्स यू आर
Atheist. You don’t believe in Islam.
एथिस्ट। आप इस्लाम में विश्वास नहीं करते।
You are not believing in Allah. You
आप अल्लाह को नहीं मान रहे हैं। आप
Don't believe in Sikhism.
सिखिज्म में विश्वास नहीं कर रहे।
I am not doing it in Buddhism. African Banging
बुद्धिज्म में नहीं कर रहे। अफ्रीकी किसी
I am not doing it in religion. stay in india
धर्म में नहीं कर रहे। भारत में ही रहने
The surnames are not in the code. you india
वाले सरनाम कोड में नहीं कर रहे। आप भारत
We are not doing it in the religion of the tribals.
के आदिवासियों के धर्म में नहीं कर रहे।
You are 399 out of 400, even you are not sure
आप 400 में से 399 में तो आप भी यकीन नहीं
are doing it. We are doing it in the same way. I
कर रहे हैं। एक ही में तो कर रहे हैं। मैं
I'm not doing it in even one of those. Bus
एक में भी उस एक में भी नहीं कर रहा। बस
That's the only difference. a while ago we
इतना ही तो अंतर है। हमने कुछ देर पहले
Talked about privilege. then there are some
प्रिविलेज की बात करी। फिर देयर आर सम
People where 10 out of 10 points are privileged
पीपल जहां 10ों के 10 पॉइंट प्रिविलेज
come to the section
सेक्शन में आ
Will go. People I've met through the show.
जाएंगे। शो के थ्रू जो लोग मिले हैं।
International guests too who are the richest and
इंटरनेशनल गेस्ट्स भी जो सबसे अमीर और
The most evolved, the most powerful, the most successful
सबसे इवॉल्व सबसे पावरफुल सबसे सक्सेसफुल
There are people who can do this. Others
लोग होते हैं ना वो यह कर पाते हैं। दूसरे
Apathy towards religion Yes but that's also n
धर्म के प्रति एमथी यस बट दैट्स आल्सो एन
The Outcome of Huge Privilege. Hughes
आउटकम ऑफ़ ह्यूज प्रिविलेज। ह्यूज
Privilege agreed but at the same time please
प्रिविलेज एग्रीड बट एट द सेम टाइम प्लीज
Understand what it is always going to be
अंडरस्टैंड इट्स इट इज़ ऑलवेज गोइंग टू बी
Easy to hate. We would be the easiest to hate.
इजी टू हेट। हम नफरत करना सबसे आसान होगा।
well why is it that we assume
अच्छा ऐसा क्यों होता है कि हम मान लीजिए
I believe in this religion. I am not
मैं मैं ए धर्म को मानता हूं। मैं नहीं
I believe but suppose I follow this religion
मानता लेकिन मान लीजिए मैं ए धर्म को
I agree. Yes and I believe in that religion
मानता हूं। जी और उस धर्म में मेरा भरोसा
Is. I also respect him. But B
है। उसकी मैं इज्जत भी करता हूं। लेकिन बी
My attitude towards the religion which I do not believe in
धर्म जिसे मैं नहीं मानता उसके प्रति मेरे
not only is there despondency inside but it could be
अंदर ना केवल नासदगी है बल्कि हो सकता है
I hate it. Where could this have come from? this this thing
नफरत है। ये कहां से आया होगा? ये इस बात
May have come from. Mostly it must have come from this
से आया हो। मोस्टली इस बात से आया होगा
because either I was told that from a
क्योंकि या तो मुझे यह बताया गया कि ए से
The condition of loving someone is that you are a
मोहब्बत करने की शर्त है कि तुम ए के
I hate or dislike everyone else. either
अलावा सबसे नांदगी या नफरत करो। या तो
I have been told this. It could be someone
मुझे यह बताया गया हो। हो सकता है किसी
It may be done in religion. Or I can call B
धर्म में किया जाता हो। या फिर मैं बी को
I don't know it. We are strangers. stranger kiss
जानता ही नहीं। हम अपरिचय है। अपरिचय किस
produces the thing? creates fear.
चीज को पैदा करता है? भय को पैदा करता है।
Because where did religions originate from? those
क्योंकि धर्म कहां से पैदा हुए? उन्हीं
Born from tribes, right? Tribals
कबीलों से पैदा हुए ना? ट्राइबल्स
Born from tribes, right? we are all tribals
ट्राइब्स से पैदा हुए ना। हम सब ट्राइबल्स
It was there only. So this was the condition in the tribes.
ही तो थे ना। तो ट्राइब्स में ये शर्त थी।
If you want to survive, you have to stay alive.
अगर आपको बचे रहना है, जिंदा बचना है।
This is a fight for survival if you are the other
अस्तित्व की लड़ाई है ये कि अगर आप दूसरे
The people of the tribe do not suspect him
कबीले के लोगों को उसके प्रति संदेह नहीं
If you keep it, and don't doubt it, then it will never tell you
रखोगे, शक नहीं रखोगे तो वह कभी भी आपको
can finish it. This fear is actually due to unfamiliarity
खत्म कर सकते हैं। यह भय दरअसल अपरिचय से
Is born. If you work very hard,
पैदा होता है। अगर आप बहुत मेहनत करें,
If you try very consciously, then
अगर आप बहुत कॉन्शियसली कोशिश करें, तो
You can probably get the most equal distance. But
संभव है कि आप सबसे बराबर दूरी पा लें। बट
In most cases you have an attachment to one
अधिकांश मामलों में आप एक के प्रति लगाव
and unfortunately for everyone else
रखते हैं और दुर्भाग्य से बाकी सबके प्रति
Al attachment is developed. i feel kit
अल लगाव पैदा हो जाता है। आई फील कित
Whatever experiences of life
जिंदगी के जितने भी एक्सपीरियंसेस रहे हैं
No, I mean I knew that at a young age I had a lot of
ना मतलब आई नो कि कम उम्र में मैंने बहुत
I have seen something. I'm not just talking
कुछ देख लिया है। आई एम नॉट जस्ट टॉकिंग
About the control. i am also talking
अबाउट द कंट्रोल। आई एम आल्सो टॉकिंग
About all the good stuff. Definitely. Gin
अबाउट ऑल द गुड स्टफ। डेफिनेटली। जिन
I have met people. I came from my own idol
लोगों से मैं मिला हूं। आई खुद के आइडल से
Whatever dreams I had in my heart during college
मैं जो भी सपने मेरे दिल में थे कॉलेज के
all of which were completed by the time I was 26 or
दौरान वो सब पूरे हो चुके थे एट एज 26 या
27 I'm 32 now so I've lived a very long time
27 आई एम 32 नाउ तो आई हैव लिव्ड अ वेरी
Nice 10 years of my career were difficult
नाइस 10 इयर्स ऑफ माय करियर मुश्किल था
Career Butt
करियर बट
There were many good moments in these 10 years
बहुत अच्छे मोमेंट्स थे इन 10 सालों
The best of all these good moments in
में इन सारे अच्छे मोमेंट्स में से बेस्ट
Moments not life changing travel based
मोमेंट्स ना लाइफ चेंजिंग ट्रैवल बेस्ड
moments were right means this is the peak of the
मोमेंट्स थे राइट मतलब ये पीक ऑफ द
Privileges Peak of the Experiences Peak
प्रिविलेजेस पीक ऑफ द एक्सपीरियंसेस पीक
of the blessings the travel experiences
ऑफ द ब्लेसिंग्स थे ट्रेवल एक्सपीरियंसेस
When I go out and meet other people
जब मैं कहीं और जाकर दूसरे लोगों से मिलता
There Privately Podcast Without Camera
वहां प्राइवेटली कैमरे के बिना पॉडकास्ट
would have done it
कर लेता
those were the moments that really expanded
दोज़ वर द मोमेंट्स दैट रियली एक्सपेंडेड
My brain, why does traveling make us generous?
माय ब्रेन ये ट्रेवलिंग हमें उदार क्यों
Just think about it, this happens
बनाती है जरा इस पे विचार कीजिए ऐसा होता
isn't it so when you travel
है ना कि आप आप जब ट्रेवल करते हैं तो
Actually you believe that you learn a lot from here
दरअसल यू बिलीव दैट यू लर्न अ लॉट ये कहां
this happens only because of this i am
से होता है ये सिर्फ इस वजह से होता आई एम
Just saying that this gives you the same starting point
जस्ट सेइंग कि यह आपको वही शुरुआती बात यह
Teaches you how to un-judge people. At home
आपको लोगों को अनज करना सिखाता है। घर में
living in a city living in a town
इस एक शहर में रहते हुए एक कस्बे में रहते
While living in the village, the more
हुए गांव में रहते हुए जिस जितनी ज्यादा
The smaller the unit, the more you will
छोटी यूनिट होती जाएगी उतना ज्यादा आपके
The responsibility of being judgemental comes upon us
ऊपर जजमेंटल होने की जिम्मेदारी आती
will remain. I told the girl that if she
रहेगी। मैंने कहा ना लड़की से कि अगर वो
You will leave the town and come to Delhi city
आप कस्बे से निकल के दिल्ली शहर आ जाओगे
So this will be freedom for you. because there
तो ये आपके लिए आजादी होगी। क्योंकि वहां
You can do or see such things happening
आप ऐसी चीजें कर पाओगे या होते हुए देखोगे
Who are considered bad in your town.
जिनको आपके कस्बे में बुरा कहा जाता है।
Don't leave the house at 7:00. told the girl
7:00 बजे घर से मत निकलो। लड़की से कहा
Will you go? Don't leave the house at 6:30. 7 You
जाएगा ना 6:30 बजे घर से मत निकलो। 7 आप
When you reach the city you will be told no
शहर में पहुंचेंगे तो आपसे कहा जाएगा नहीं
You can stay till 10:00. a little bit right now
आप 10:00 बजे तक रह सकते। थोड़ा सा अभी
It did not happen that you became completely free.
ऐसा नहीं हुआ कि आपको पूरे आजाद हो गए।
But your horizons rose a little. you are abroad
लेकिन थोड़ा सा आपका होरजन बढ़ा। आप विदेश
If you go, you will find out whether or not the girl is on top of you
जाएंगे तो पता लगेगा कि नहीं लड़की के ऊपर
What does curfew timing mean? When
कर्फ्यू टाइमिंग का क्या मतलब है? जब
You can go as you wish. Yes. Ok. you learn to unz
मर्जी निकलो। जी। ठीक है। यू लर्न टू अनज
Because all those things which are prohibited in your place
बिकॉज़ वो सारी चीजें जो आपके यहां निषेध
Were. Those things which you feel bad about
थे। वो चीजें जिन जिनको आपके यहां बुरा
It is believed. The things that you have here
माना जाता है। वो चीजें जिनके यहां आपके
There is a prohibition above which is considered bad. You
ऊपर वर्जना है जो बुरी मानी जाती है। आप
find that in other societies they have to face as much
पाते हैं कि दूसरे समाजों में उन्हें उतना
It is not considered bad. then it's in your mind
बुरा नहीं माना जाता। फिर आपके मन में ये
The question arises that why is it bad for me here
सवाल उठता है कि यार मेरे यहां बुरा क्यों
It is believed? You were a little critical
माना जाता है? आप थोड़ा सा क्रिटिकल होते
Are. I'm right or wrong but you
हैं। मैं सही गलत किसी भी लेकिन आप हो
Even after that you might still consider him bad
सकता है उसके बाद भी आप उसे बुरा ही मानते
are. But at least he should be allowed to tolerate it
रहे। लेकिन कम से कम उसे टोलरेट करने की
Your capacity will increase because you will know
आपकी क्षमता बढ़ जाएगी क्योंकि आपको पता
that is acceptable in any other society. So
है कि किसी और समाज में स्वीकार्य है। तो
You will not believe that those who live in my society
आप यह नहीं मानेंगे कि जो मेरे समाज में
It is said that everything is fine. Brother
कहा जाता है वही सब कुछ ठीक है। भाई
In Afghanistan, any capable man has this
अफगानिस्तान में किसी बाकायदा पुरुष को यह
if his wife is according to him then he has the right
हक है कि अगर उसकी स्त्री उसके हिसाब से
If it's not working then kill her. kill him
नहीं चल रही तो उसकी हत्या कर दे। उसे मार
Put it. For honor, some from our country too
डाले। ऑनर के लिए हमारे देश के भी कुछ
These cases of honour killing are heard in some parts
हिस्सों में ये ऑनर किलिंग सुनने को मिलती
Was. You go abroad and you see that
थी। आप विदेश जाएं और आप देखें कि ऐसे
This is a society in which a girl is ignored for her body
समाज है जिसमें लड़की अपनी बॉडी के लिए
She can decide for her own relationship.
अपने रिलेशनशिप के लिए खुद तय कर सकती है।
When you see that you will know that it is an honour killing
जब आप उसे देखेंगे तो आप जो ऑनर किलिंग है
Will you raise a question on that or not? You
उस पर सवाल उठाएंगे कि नहीं उठाएंगे? आप
You will pick it up and say that friend it is his life.
उठाएंगे आप कहेंगे कि यार उसकी जिंदगी है।
She has the right to decide who she wants to be with
उसको तय करने का हक है कि वो किसके साथ
Will she go? Whom will she marry, whom will she marry
जाएगी? किस-किस से शादी करेगी, किससे शादी
I will not do any relationship with whom
नहीं करेगी, किसके साथ से रिलेशनशिप
She will make it, it is her right. when you think like this
बनाएगी, यह उसका हक है। जब आप ऐसा सोचना
Let's start with, where did this come from? It is then
शुरू करते हैं, तो यह कहां से आया? यह तब
came when you saw the bigger world and
आया जब आपने ज्यादा बड़ी दुनिया देखी और
You have given bias to your previous planets
आपने जो आपके पूर्व ग्रह थे उन्हें बायसेस
You started eliminating those that were there.
जो थे उन्हें आपने खत्म करना शुरू किया।
This is why traveling makes us generous
इसलिए ट्रेवलिंग हमें इसलिए उदार बनाती है
Because it's also true that we can control our prejudices
क्योंकि इट अलस कि हम अपने प्रिजुडिसिस को
Ask questions. I think at every turn of life
क्वेश्चन करें। आई थिंक जिंदगी के हर मोड़
But you don't have to define your own life.
पर ना आप खुद की जिंदगी को डिफाइन करने की
Do you try? It's just an overthinking brain
कोशिश करते हो। ये बस एक ओवरथिंकिंग ब्रेन
is the outcome.
की आउटकम है।
that again from the same intellectual base that if
कि अगेन फिर से वही बौद्धिक आलय से कि अगर
Suppose we see something unusual and we want to
मान लीजिए हमने कुछ अनूठा देखा और हम उसे
If you are not able to justify this then we
जस्टिफाई नहीं कर पा रहे जी तो हमें ये
Looks like something is wrong. then we are nobody
लगता है गड़बड़ है। फिर हम कोई ना कोई
also formulate theories that would help them
सिद्धांत भी तैयार करते हैं जिससे वो
You should be justified. at this point in life
जस्टिफाई हो। एट दिस पॉइंट जिंदगी के इस
After reaching the turn, I realized that
मोड़ तक पहुंचने के बाद मैंने ये जाना है
that I am working hard on myself first
कि मैं मेहनत कर रहा हूं पहले तो खुद के
For the family and the team is also in the family
परिवार के लिए एंड परिवार में टीम भी
Is included. Ok? that surrounds me
शामिल है। ठीक है? जो आसपास की मेरी खुद
of my tribe my people for whom every day is my
की ट्राइब मेरे लोग जिनके लिए हर दिन मेरी
Eyes open for them but the personal selfishness
आंख खुलती है फॉर देम बट द पर्सनल सेल्फिश
The angle of working hard is travel so that I
एंगल ऑफ वर्किंग हार्ड इज़ ट्रेवल ताकि मैं
can I afford the travel
ट्रेवल को अफोर्ड कर पाऊं
Actually I am hungry to study and
एक्चुअली मैं अ पढ़ाई के लिए भूखा हूं और
My life is best because of studies and not traveling
मेरी जिंदगी बेस्ट पढ़ाई ना ट्रेवल के
during this time you are absolutely great yes books
दौरान हो एक्साक्ट्ली ग्रेट हां किताबों
without the podcast without the people on
के बिना पॉडकास्ट के बिना पर लोगों के
through think the exact opposite think that he
थ्रू इसका ठीक विपरीत सोचिए सोचिए कि वह
Society that said don't travel. Our
समाज जिसने कहा कि ट्रेवल मत करो। हमारा
This country was once a society whose
ही देश एक समय तक ऐसा समाज था जिसके
The rules said that you should not travel. He
नियमों में था कि आप ट्रेवल मत करो। वह
The person who crosses the ocean will be called a brotherhood
व्यक्ति जो समंदर पार जाएगा उसे बिरादरी
should be removed from. It is our society’s
से निकाल दिया जाए। यह हमारे समाज के
It was in principles. What did he want? They
सिद्धांतों में था। वो क्या चाहता था? वो
Maybe it wanted you not to open your eyes.
शायद यह चाहता था कि आपकी आंखें ना खुले।
He probably wanted you to be free from prejudice
वो शायद यह चाहता था कि आप प्रिजुडिसिस से
You should not be free. He probably wanted you to
फ्री ना हो। वो शायद यह चाहता था कि आप
Don't be free, learn it. that's why next
आजाद ना हो सीखें ना। दैट्स व्हाई अगली
for the next generation for the next generation we
जनरेशन के लिए अगले अगली पीढ़ी के लिए हम
People should ensure that the
लोगों को ये एनश्योर करना चाहिए कि जो
There are boundaries which we call national
बाउंड्रीज हैं जो जिस जिन्हें हम नेशनल
Boundaries are called state boundaries
बाउंड्रीज कहते हैं, स्टेट की बाउंड्री
It is said that it is the boundary of language
कहते हैं, लैंग्वेज की बाउंड्री कहते हैं
And so on. These boundaries are actually the thinking
वगैरह-वगैरह। ये बाउंड्रीज दरअसल यही सोच
There would be boundaries to restrict only
को ही रेस्ट्रिक्ट करने की बाउंड्रीज होती
Are. Get free from them once and for all. One
हैं। एक बार इनसे निकल के आजाद होइए। एक
So affordability is an issue in itself.
तो अफोर्डेबिलिटी अपने आप में एक इशू है।
But be free from it. you are a better person
लेकिन एक उससे आजाद होइए। आप बेहतर इंसान
Will be made. Would you like to read this whole podcast?
बनेंगे। वुड यू से कि इस पूरे पॉडकास्ट की
The core message is that if you have more experience in your career
कोर मैसेज यह है कि अगर करियर में ज्यादा
In an era where we have to move forward rapidly
तेजी से आगे बढ़ना है एक ऐसे जमाने में
Where everyone is working hard. Then
जहां हर कोई मेहनत कर रहा है। तो फिर
Street smarts are needed, Self
स्ट्रीट स्मार्ट्स की जरूरत है, सेल्फ
Awareness is needed, maturity is needed
अवेयरनेस की जरूरत है, मैच्योरिटी की
There is need.
जरूरत है।
Well, all these things are needed. all of these
वेल ये सारी चीजों की जरूरत है। इन सारी
Things have their own processes which
चीजों के के अपने प्रोसेससेस हैं जिन
Through whom this will be decided. But my message is this
जिनसे ये तय होगा। बट मेरा मैसेज इससे
There is a little bit more. this thing in that message
थोड़ा सा और भी है। उस मैसेज में ये चीज
This also includes those who are likely to succeed rapidly.
भी शामिल है कि ये जो तेजी से सफल होने की
We have an aspiration, a little question on this too
आकांक्षा है हम इस पर भी थोड़ा सा सवाल
pick him up a little bit that critically
उठाना उसको भी थोड़ा सा उस क्रिटिकली
It is equally important to see this as
देखना ये भी उतना ही जरूरी है जितना कि
something else because Ranveer think about this
कुछ और क्योंकि रणवीर सोच के देखिए यह बात
It is true that having fame, having money, moving forward
सही है कि फेम का होना, पैसे का होना, आगे
Who would not want to grow? To all
बढ़ना इसकी इच्छा किसे नहीं होगी। सभी को
It must be happening. But is this the ultimate purpose?
होती होगी। लेकिन क्या ये अल्टीमेट पर्पस
of life does it give? Is this what life is
ऑफ़ लाइफ देता है क्या? क्या यही जिंदगी की
Is there any meaning? There will be something besides this
सार्थकता है क्या? इसके अलावा भी कुछ होगी
No? Because Hitler had everything.
ना? क्योंकि हिटलर के पास तो सब कुछ था।
This was also famous. Everybody is listening to him
ये फेम भी था। सारे लोग उसकी सुन भी रहे
Were. He doesn't like the people who were his own
थे। जो लोग उसके अपने थे वो उसे पसंद नहीं
used to do it. There were people dying for him.
करते थे। देयर वर पीपल डाइंग फॉर हिम।
Right? Was Hitler's life purposeful?
राइट? क्या हिटलर की जिंदगी पर्पसफुल
What was life? I'm sure you will agree
जिंदगी थी क्या? आई एम श्योर यू विल एग्री
That it was not. so the ultimate purpose is
दैट इट वाज़ नॉट। सो अल्टीमेट पर्पस जो है
He is not the only one who can ensure quick success
वो केवल यह श्योर श क्विक सक्सेस को नहीं
It can be considered. We need to go beyond that.
माना जा सकता। वी नीड टू गो बियोंड दैट।
If you ask me I would like to
मैं अगर आप मुझसे पूछे जैसे मेरे लिए
What is succulence? I will say two things. Forest
सक्सेस क्या है? आई विल से टू थिंग्स। वन
Is this how much respect? how much respect you
इज़ हाउ मच रिस्पेक्ट। हाउ मच रिस्पेक्ट यू
Earn, Respect, Attention, Influence
अर्न, रिस्पेक्ट, अटेंशन, इन्फ्लुएंस
From People Unlike You? who is not like you
फ्रॉम पीपल अनलाइक यू? जो आप जैसे नहीं
Is. Is it okay? that is one marker and
है। ठीक है ना? दैट इज वन मार्कर एंड
second marker and i'm giving something
सेकंड मार्कर एंड आई एम गिविंग समथिंग
Controversial. second marker is how much
कंट्रोवर्शियल। सेकंड मार्कर इज हाउ मच
Dislike and sometimes hate but hate is too harsh
डिसलाइक और समटाइम हेट बट हेट इज टू हार्श
The word sometimes how much you dislike it you get from
वर्ड समटाइम हाउ मच डिसलाइक यू गेट फ्रॉम
The People Like You for the Privileges of
द पीपल लाइक यू फॉर द प्रिविलेजेस ऑफ
Yours. That is also to me. In my view
योर्स। दैट इज आल्सो टू मी। मेरी नजर में
It is also a marker of how much you
यह भी एक मार्कर है इस बात का कि आप कितने
Think about Gandhiji while travelling.
सफर में गांधी जी के बारे में सोचिए।
Gandhiji is a rich variety of Gujarat
गांधी जी गुजरात के संपन्न संपन्न किस्म
He was a person coming from the families of. Character
के परिवारों से आने वाले व्यक्ति थे। वर्ण
He was a person coming from a Varnik family.
वर्णिक परिवार से आने वाले व्यक्ति थे।
But who respected Gandhiji? Mango
लेकिन गांधी जी की इज्जत किसने की? आम
The poor man. Other people did. Ok
गरीब व्यक्ति ने। दूसरे लोगों ने। ठीक है
No? who were not like him. The Muslims
ना? जो उनके जैसे नहीं थे। मुसलमानों ने
the other British they were fighting
दूसरे अंग्रेजों ने जिनसे वो लड़ रहे थे
other people who were not like them
दूसरे लोगों ने जो उन जैसे नहीं थे उन
People respected him while his own people
लोगों ने उनकी इज्जत की जबकि उनके अपने
People in the community were not very happy. Correct
समुदाय के लोग बहुत प्रसन्न नहीं थे। ठीक
Isn't it? To me, this is a marker for me.
है ना? टू मी मेरे लिए ये मार्कर है।
So when I'm including my
इसलिए जब मैं अपने से शामिल कर रहा हूं
That's why I am saying this. so when the people who tell me
इसलिए कह रहा हूं। इसलिए जब वे लोग जो मुझ
Like he is not respectful to me
जैसे नहीं है वो मेरे लिए रिस्पेक्टफुल
There are. He respects me. me me
होते हैं। मेरी इज्जत करते हैं। मुझे मुझे
Gives identification. I feel happy. But
पहचान देते हैं। मुझे खुशी होती है। लेकिन
Probably happier than when people
शायद उससे ज्यादा खुशी होती है जब लोग
I love those who are like me
मुझे जो मेरे जैसे हैं मेरे जैसे
come from from from backgrounds.
बैकग्राउंड से पृष्ठभूमियों से आते हैं।
Which started around me. no i
जिनकी शुरुआत मेरे आसपास हुई। नहीं मैं
I'm going beyond that. I am social
मैं उससे ज्यादा जा रहा हूं। मैं सोशल
I am going to the categories. Nowadays I like most
कैटेगरीज में जा रहा हूं। मुझे आजकल सबसे
Which people troll the most? Those people
ज्यादा कौन से लोग ट्रोल करते हैं? वे लोग
Who are people with upper caste privilege
जो कि अपर कास्ट प्रिविलेज वाले लोग हैं
And in what sense does it cost that this
और किस सेंस में कॉस्ट करते हैं कि यह
The person speaks against the upper caste. it
व्यक्ति अपर कास्ट के खिलाफ बोलता है। यह
Individuals against these social categories
व्यक्ति इन इन सोशल कैटेगरीज के खिलाफ
He speaks. Do I come from these categories.
बोलता है। दो आई कम फ्रॉम दीज़ कैटेगरीज।
It is a point to be noted. what about me
इट इज अ पॉइंट टू बी नोटेड। मुझे क्या
You will be abused that whatever lower caste you are
गालियां दी जाएंगी कि आप जो भी लोअर कास्ट
All those names are abused for
के लिए गालियां दी जाती है उन सबका नाम
Taking it as given that you talk about them. You
लेते हुए कि तुम तो उनकी बात करते हो। तुम
You are like them. A lot of people believe that
उन जैसे हो। बहुत सारे लोग तो यकीन करते
that I probably fall into those categories
हैं कि मैं शायद उन्हीं कैटेगरीज से आता
Am. This to me is a medal. which means that
हूं। दिस टू मी इज अ मेडल। इसका मतलब जो
Like people come to share my privileges
जैसे लोग मेरे प्रिविलेजेस को शेयर करने
people are disliking me
वाले लोग मुझसे मुझे नापसंद कर रहे हैं
Because I speak against those privileged people
क्योंकि मैं उन प्रिविलजेस के खिलाफ बोल
From which I come and from me
रहा हूं जिनमें से मैं आता हूं और मुझसे
Different people reject me or
भिन्न लोग मुझे रिसेक्ट देते हैं या मुझे
I like it. Dispite the fact that I
पसंद करते हैं। डिस्पाइट द फैक्ट कि मैं
I am different from them. To me this is success. This
उनसे भिन्न हूं। टू मी दिस इज सक्सेस। दिस
Attention can always be monetized also. You
अटेंशन कैन ऑलवेज बी मोनेटाइज आल्सो। यू
No attention once you have the money
नो अटेंशन एक बार आपके पास है उसे पैसा
It is a very easy and quick process to make, I am an agency
बनाना तो चुटकी चुटकियों का देर एजेंसी हु
Rush to that sir you have so much attention.
रश टू कि सर आपके पास इतनी अटेंशन है।
Do you have 10 million followers or
आपके पास 1 करोड़ फॉलोवर्स हैं या आपके
There are so many subscribers. we will give you that
इतने सब्सक्राइबर हैं। वी विल गिव यू दैट
Cat of Money. That is an easy part of it. So
कैट ऑफ़ मनी। दैट इज़ अ ईजी पार्ट ऑफ़ इट। सो
Mot monetization will get money, fame,
मोट मोनेटाइजेशन पैसा मिलेगा, फेम मिलेगा,
you will get some identity is it will come
यू विल गेट सम आइडेंटिटी इस इस इट विल कम
In due course. That means I am not not
इन ड्यू कोर्स। वो मतलब आई एम नॉट नॉट
Saying it's wrong. I'm not even saying that
सेइंग इट्स रोंग। मैं ये भी नहीं कह रहा
This is a bad thing. Should not do. But he
ये बुरी चीज़ है। नहीं करनी चाहिए। पर वो
so once you have this attention and respect come
तो वंस यू हैव दिस अटेंशन एंड रिस्पेक्ट आ
It will go away. I think again sir a very free
ही जाएगी। आई थिंक अगेन सर एक बहुत फ्री
I've been writing this entire podcast from a position of flow.
फ्लो के पोजीशन से मैंने इस पूरे पॉडकास्ट
had started. This was an unplanned podcast.
की शुरुआत करी थी। अनप्लंड पडकास्ट था यह।
but i new i am going to talk about the
बट आई न्यू आई एम गोइंग टू टॉक अबाउट द
The Human Journey and Maturity Mainly. it
ह्यूमन जर्नी एंड मैच्योरिटी मेनली। यह
It was my theme. I'm just sharing one thing
मेरी थीम थी। मैं बस एक चीज शेयर करना
And then you can shed light on it.
चाहूंगा एंड देन यू कैन शेड लाइट ऑन इट।
A: They say that the five people around you
अ कहते हैं ना कि आपके आसपास के जो पांच
There are people, you become an average of them. The
लोग हैं आप उनका एक एवरेज बन जाते हो। द
People you spend time. It is a great truth
पीपल यू स्पेंड टाइम। बहुत बड़ा सत्य है
Of life. And the game is to have a bit of
जिंदगी का। एंड द गेम इज टू हैव अ बिट ऑफ़
Rotation in those five people. as you keep
रोटेशन इन दोज़ फाइव पीपल। एज यू कीप
Growing Older. Little Things Like When You're
ग्रोइंग ओल्डर। लिटिल थिंग्स लाइक जब आप
with people older than you
अपने उम्र से ज्यादा उम्र के लोगों के साथ
Spend time getting to know their personality
वक्त बिताते हो उनकी पर्सनालिटी के
Some things rub off on you.
कुछ-कुछ चीजें आप पे रब ऑफ हो जाते हैं।
and i think it's wonderful for everyone
एंड आई थिंक इट्स वेरीेंट फॉर एव्री
Human beings like to hang out with older people.
ह्यूमन बीइंग टू हैंग आउट विथ ओल्डर पीपल।
A very simple career hack
अ ये एक बहुत सिंपल करियर हैक है
Actually. If you can lead the learnings into
एक्चुअली। इफ यू कैन लीड द लर्निंग्स इंटू
Your career. a that's the final thing i want
योर करियर। अ दैट्स द फाइनल थिंग आई वांट
To say in this hole algorithm. because here
टू से इन दिस होल एल्गोरिदम। क्योंकि यहां
We have drawn out a maturity algorithm
हमने एक मैच्योरिटी का एल्गोरिदम ड्रॉ आउट
I have told him to do this exercise
कर दिया है कि ये एक्सरसाइज करो वो
Do exercise. But I feel that someone is different from you
एक्सरसाइज करो। बट आई फील कि कोई जो आपसे
big one is the one with whom you have fun and who
बड़ा है जिसके साथ आपको मजा आता है और जो
Challenges you with a growth mindset
आपको चैलेंज करता है ग्रोथ मेंटालिटी वाला
Tell me the time individually with them.
इंडिविजुअल उनके साथ टाइम बताओ।
Well Ranbir for the first time in this
वेल रणबीर फॉर द फर्स्ट टाइम इन दिस
Conversation happened for the first time so late
कन्वर्सेशन फर्स्ट टाइम पूरे इतनी देर से
In conversation. I mean I saw your beach facing
बातचीत में। आई मीन आई सॉ योर बीच फेसिंग
Balcony. I saw this seven camera setup. I
बालकनी। आई सॉ दिस सेवन कैमरा सेटअप। आई
Saw This Wonderful Studio Everything Not Even
सॉ दिस वंडरफुल स्टूडियो एवरीथिंग नॉट इवन
once i had this element in me thinking
वंस आई हैड दिस एलिमेंट इन मी थिंकिंग
about you this is the first time having a
अबाउट यू दिस इज द फर्स्ट टाइम हैविंग अ
In Person
पर्सन इन योर
Life that is yours can criticize you
लाइफ जो आपका आपका आपकी आलोचना कर सकता है
A little bit of panic can also cause a crisis to occur
थोड़ा बहुत हड़का भी सकता है संकट आने में
It also hides
छुपा भी लेता है
and this is the first time i am having this
और दिस इज द फर्स्ट टाइम आई एम हैविंग दिस
Element of Envy
एलिमेंट ऑफ एनवी
I mean this is a personal thing that I
मतलब दिस इज अ पर्सनल थिंग कि मैंने
Records of losing good friends in life
जिंदगी में अच्छे दोस्त खोने के रिकॉर्ड
Have made it. Ok? continuously one after the other
बनाए हैं। ठीक है? लगातार एक के बाद एक
good
अच्छे
maybe my friend
दोस्त शायद मेरी
Just like you said, there are many foolish things of mine
ही मेरी ही जैसे आपने कहा ना मूर्खताएं कई
It happens many times or sometimes you have to take tough decisions
कई बार होती है या कभी आप कड़े फैसले लेने
I get scared. Some of you make those decisions
में डर जाते हैं। कुछ आपको आप वो फैसले
You are not able to take what you should take. and you
नहीं ले पाते जो आपको लेने चाहिए। एंड यू
End up paying the price. ah so i totally
एंड अप पेइंग प्राइस। अह सो आई टोटली
Agree when you say that having friends
एग्री व्हेन यू से दैट हैविंग फ्रेंड्स
especially the friends who have the ability to
स्पेशली द फ्रेंड्स हु हैव एबिलिटी टू
critic you and as you said you said you
क्रिटिक यू एंड एस यू सेड आपने कहा कि आप
This is another big achievement for a little bigger than
से थोड़े से बड़े ये एक और बड़ी उपलब्धि
because you are with them and you are with them
है क्योंकि आप उनके साथ हैं और आप उनसे
I am learning. There is nothing unique about this
सीख रहे हैं। इसमें तो कुछ कोई अनूठी बात
It doesn't exist. But he makes you feel worth it
है ही नहीं। लेकिन वो आपको इस लायक लगातार
I am able to share this with you
पा रहे हैं कि आपके साथ ये शेयरिंग हो
It can. Little Mature Still Believing
सकती है। लिटिल मैच्योर स्टिल बिलीविंग
And for a very long period of time. it
एंड फॉर अ वेरी लॉन्ग पीरियड ऑफ़ टाइम। यह
There is a blessing, a blessing that you
एक ऐसी नेमत है, एक ऐसी नेमत है जिसे आपको
It should be kept absolutely safe. and that means i
एकदम बचा के रखना चाहिए। और मतलब मैं तो
You said that I am an atheist
आपने मैंने कहा कि मैं तो नास्तिक आदमी
Am. I don't believe in all these things
हूं। नहीं करता इन सब चीजों में यकीन
But even then, if the evil eye falls on you
लेकिन फिर भी अगर कभी नजर लगती होगी तो
It will be focused on this thing only. believe in everything else
इसी चीज पे लगेगी। बाकी चीजों पर यकीन
Do it, it doesn't matter. I came and wished that your
कीजिए नहीं लगे। वो मैं आई विश कि आपके
it remains large and grows but if that
पास ये बड़ी बनी रहे और बढ़े लेकिन अगर वो
Even if it doesn't happen, if you are able to hold
नहीं भी हो तब भी इफ यू आर एबल टू होल्ड
on to this particular thing i mean it is
ऑन टू दिस पर्टिकुलर थिंग आई मीन इट इज
Worth holding. Ok? so this never plays
वर्थ होल्डिंग। ठीक है? सो दिस नेवर प्ले
Musical chairs with this aspect. it's not
म्यूजिकल चेयर विद दिस अस्पेक्ट। इट्स नॉट
A thing that you should be testing every day.
अ थिंग दैट यू यू शुड बी टेस्टिंग एवरीडे।
Ok? If You Have Been Tested Once or Twice
ठीक है? इफ यू हैव टेस्टेड वंस और ट्वाइस
In the life that much is enough. Good Friends
इन द लाइफ दैट मच इज इनफ। अच्छे दोस्तों
Hold on to it. but infact i am
को पकड़ कर रखिए। बल्कि इनफैक्ट आई एम
taking this opportunity to say sorry to all
टेकिंग दिस अपॉर्चुनिटी टू से सॉरी टू ऑल
my friends who consider that rightly and
माय फ्रेंड्स हु कंसीडर दैट राइटली और
wrongly they believe that i have been unfair to
रोंगली दे बिलीव दैट आई हैव बीन अनफेयर टू
Them.
देम।
Because it is such an achievement if you have
बिकॉज़ यह एक ऐसी उपलब्धि है अगर आपके पास
There are some friends like this and there are only a few like this
ऐसे कुछ दोस्त हैं और ऐसे कुछ ही होने
Needed It cannot be 100 50 150 200.
चाहिए। यह 100 50 150 200 नहीं हो सकते।
There can be 100 50 150 200 quants. They
100 50 150 200 एक्वेंट्स हो सकते हैं। वो
It may also contribute to your life
भी हो सकता है आपकी जिंदगी को कंट्रीब्यूट
Do it. I am not at all denying that. But
करें। आई एम नॉट एट ऑल डिनाइंग दैट। लेकिन
Friends who catch you and criticize you
ऐसे दोस्त जो आपको पकड़ कर आपकी आलोचना कर
and in that criticism you may once again think
सकें और उस आलोचना में आपके मन में एक बार
It also does not appear that there is anything behind this criticism
भी यह नहीं आए कि इस आलोचना के पीछे कुछ
There are ulterior motives. this is a prized
अल्टीरियर मोटिव्स हैं। दिस इज अ प्राइस्ड
Position. so please have my nva
पोजीशन। सो प्लीज हैव माय एनवीए
And blessings oh that's what there is
एंड आशीर्वाद ओह दैट दैट इज देयर
After the crisis, it would value it even more
संकट के बाद ना और भी ज्यादा वैल्यू करता
I am please do friendship why so many times
हूं मैं दोस्ती को प्लीज डू क्यों इतने
all the people are gone the ones that stay you love them
सारे लोग चले गए द वंस दैट स्टे यू लव देम
The Once I Had Nobody to Give Many Sure
द वंस आई आई हैव नोबडी टू गिव मेनी श्योर
shots and nobody to give you advice but
शॉट्स एंड नोबडी टू गिव यू एडवाइस लेकिन
who left or suppose you think that
जो चले गए या मान लीजिए आपको लगता है कि
He shouldn't be standing with you
वो आपके साथ नहीं खड़े हुए होना चाहिए
Was Needed. A little sympathy for them too
चाहिए था। उनके प्रति भी थोड़ा सा एमथी
Be a little compassionate, a little generous
थोड़ा सा एमथी थोड़ा सा उदारता ही रखिए
because many times people think of us as
क्योंकि बहुत बार लोग हम लोगों को जैसे
you don't have to feel it because you
आपको नहीं महसूस करना पड़ रहा क्योंकि यू
Thankfully ideologically your placed in a
थैंकफुली आइडियोलॉजिकली योर प्लेस्ड इन अ
A place where there are less worries about this. I am
प्लेस जहां पे ये वाली चिंता कम है। आई एम
ideologically placed where these consistently
आइडियोलॉजिकली प्लेस्ड जहां पे लगातार ये
there is a concern that you
वाली चिंता होती है कि आप आपको
The establishment won't like it. To you
एस्टैब्लिशमेंट पसंद नहीं करेगा। आपको
Governments will not like it etc.
सरकारें पसंद नहीं करेंगे वगैरह-वगैरह।
That is why we know such people more closely
इसलिए हम ज्यादा क्लोजली ऐसे लोगों को
Let's see who should do what, who should say what
देखते हैं जिनको जो करना चाहिए, जो बोलना
They should avoid speaking. where stood
चाहिए वो बोलने से बचते हैं। जहां खड़ा
You should avoid standing there.
होना चाहिए वहां खड़े होने से बचते हैं।
And it is also true that this is always done out of fear.
और यह भी सच है कि हमेशा डर की वजह से ऐसा
I wouldn’t be doing it. Sometimes more than fear
नहीं कर रहे होते। कई बार डर से ज्यादा
Greed plays a big role. Some small
बड़ा रोल लालच का होता है। कुछ पा छोटी
getting some small proximities,
छोटी-छोटी कुछ कुछ प्रॉक्सिमिटीज पा जाना,
Get some benefits. but both ways it is
कुछ बेनिफिट्स पा जाना। बट बोथ वेज़ इट्स
Human It's human to be afraid. it's
ह्यूमन इट्स ह्यूमन टू बी अफ्रेड। इट्स
It's human to be a little greedy. whatever you say
ह्यूमन टू बी लिटिल ग्रीडी। जो जो आप कह
I understand theoretically that you are like this.
रहे हो ना ये मैं थ्यरेटिकली समझता हूं।
I understand but this thing is inside my heart
आई अंडरस्टैंड बट मेरे दिल के अंदर यह बात
Hasn't gone yet. I totally understand
अब तक नहीं गई है। आई आई टोटली अंडरस्टैंड
that i am saying so because as i said you
दैट आई एम सेइंग सो बिकॉज़ एज आई सेड यू
still you had friends that
हैड फ्रेंड्स स्टिल यू हैड फ्रेंड्स जो कि
Was there for you in your time of need. ever to me
आपके संकट के समय में खड़े थे। मुझे कभी
Sometimes I feel that my friends know this
कभी-कभी लगता है कि मेरे दोस्तों को यह
It might seem so. I'm sorry to say that
लगता होगा। आई एम सॉरी टू से दैट कि
When they needed Vijendra, he was there
उन्हें जब जरूरत थी तब विजेंद्र उतनी
I did not stand firmly with them. and I
मजबूती से उनके साथ नहीं खड़ा था। एंड आई
I'm taking this opportunity to say sorry to you.
एम टेकिंग दिस अपॉर्चुनिटी टू से सॉरी टू।
Do you miss anyone? Say This Is What I Mean
याद आती है किसी की? से दिस दिस आई मीन
Thfully there is no friend for whom I can do this
थफुली देयर इज नो फ्रेंड जिसके लिए मैं यह
Let me say that he dumped me. i can
कहूं कि उसने मुझे डंप कर दिया। आई कैन
not say with confidence that it is not like that
नॉट से विद कॉन्फिडेंस कि वो ऐसा नहीं
They must be saying this. so they can be us people
कहते होंगे। सो दे कैन बी हम हम लोगों
Stories is very complex.
कीिंदगियां बहुत कॉम्प्लेक्स होती हैं।
They are very complicated. simple life
बहुत कॉम्प्लिकेटेड होती हैं। सरल जिंदगी
So only in geometry notebook
तो केवल ज्योमेट्री की की नोटबुक में
is shown. in which a scale was placed and
दिखाई जाती है। जिसमें एक स्केल रखा और
Drawn it with a pencil. life's straight line
पेंसिल से खींच दी। जिंदगियां सरल रेखा
I kept walking. Sometimes I know what I
में चलती रही। कभी-कभी पता है मैं क्या
I think about the romantic breakups that happen
सोचता हूं कि जो रोमांटिक ब्रेकअप्स होते
Yes, they give you pain for some time.
हैं ना वो कुछ समय तक आपको दर्द देते हैं।
The breakups that happen between the Butt brothers
बट भाइयों के बीच जो ब्रेकअप्स होते हैं
They keep pricking you throughout your life. yes this
वो जिंदगी भर आपको चुभते रहते हैं। हां ये
and the other thing is that in our country
भी है और दूसरा यह भी है कि हमारे देश में
And you will find that just once again I am
और ये आप पाएंगे कि जरा फिर से मैं आई एम
Sorry I am taking you there again. but this
सॉरी आई एम टेकिंग यू अगेन देयर। लेकिन ये
which is the construct of friendship, this is friendship
जो दोस्ती का कंस्ट्रक्ट है ये दोस्ती का
construct of men's friendship
कंस्ट्रक्ट पुरुषों की दोस्ती का
It is constructed. How to Look Carefully
कंस्ट्रक्ट है। लुक लुक केयरफुली कैसे
Men are raised here.
हमारे यहां पुरुष खड़े किए जाते हैं।
It happens in that, isn't it, he is just a brother here
उसमें होता है ना कि एकदम भाई है यहां पे
standing. You do whatever you want to do. I am yours
खड़ा। तू कर तुझे जो करना है कर। मैं तेरे
I stand with you. The brother the friend will not judge
साथ खड़ा हूं। द भाई द दोस्त विल नॉट जज
You. Whether what you did was right or not.
यू। कि तूने जो किया वो ठीक था कि नहीं।
Was it ethical or not? Is it okay? When I my
नैतिक था कि नहीं। ठीक है ना? जब मैं मेरे
About my own friendship breakups
खुद के फ्रेंडशिप ब्रेकअप्स के बारे में
I think. especially with the brothers, those
सोचता हूं। स्पेशली भाइयों के साथ, उन
Where there was such friendship with people. So
लोगों के साथ जहां ऐसी वाली दोस्ती थी। तो
Often this thought comes to my mind that
अक्सर यह थॉट आता है मेरे दिमाग में कि
Friend, even if we patch up, the friendship remains the same
यार अगर पैचअप हो भी गया तो दोस्ती वैसी
She will not stay. But that's why maybe I need a patch up
नहीं रहेगी। बट उस वजह से शायद मुझे पैचअप
don't do it because it's here 200%
नहीं करना क्योंकि इट्स इदर 200%
And not that. You want it absolutely pure.
और नॉट दैट। एकदम प्योर चाहिए आपको।
Perfection and purity, maybe these are my emotional
परफेक्शन और प्युरिटी शायद ये मेरी इमोशनल
There is a limitation. But I did not understand. I
लिमिटेशन है। बट नहीं आई अंडरस्टैंड। आई
Am I totally respect this feeling s
एम आई आई टोटली रेस्पेक्ट दिस फीलिंग एस
True, but I have many friends like this for example.
सच बट मेरे कई दोस्त ऐसे हैं फॉर एग्जांपल
Friends with whom I spent months talking
जिन दोस्तों के साथ मेरा महीनों बातचीत
it doesn't happen, it doesn't happen for months but when again
नहीं होती महीनों नहीं होती लेकिन जब फिर
When there is a conversation, you don't have any warm up
बातचीत होती है तो आपको कोई वार्म अप नहीं
you have to start from the place where
करना पड़ता यू स्टार्ट फ्रॉम द प्लेस वेयर
you left ok and the reason is that dost
यू लेफ्ट ठीक है एंड द रीज़न इज दैट दोस्त
He will not judge you because you did 3
आपको इसलिए नहीं जज करेगा कि यार तूने 3
I did not take any care of myself for four months
महीने 4 महीने मुझे मेरी सुध नहीं ली मैं
no actually what do they say actually
ना एक्चुअली ली वो क्या कहते हैं एक्चुअल
The one who breaks up after a fight
वो जो एक झगड़े के बाद ब्रेकअप हो जाता है
no i am talking about that, that's it, it is said
ना उसकी बात कर रहा हूं दैट्स दैट इज सेड
not not losing touch losing touch wala ok
नॉट नॉट लूजिंग टच लूजिंग टच वाली ठीक है
yes not losing i was talking about
हां लूजिंग नहीं आई वास टॉकिंग अबाउट
losing touch i was not talking about fights
लूजिंग टच आई वास नॉट टॉकिंग अबाउट झगड़े
I have a bag full of friendship for those who fight
वाला झगड़े वाले दोस्ती का थफुली मेरे पास
Have less experience. Experiencing a tumultuous friendship
कम अनुभव है। झगड़े वाली दोस्ती का अनुभव
I have less. there are one or two and she teases
मेरे पास कम है। एक दो हैं वो टीस करती
Are.
हैं।
But I learn to get over this. Painfully Butt
लेकिन आई लर्न टू गेट ओवर दिस। पेनफुली बट
Coming
आई ल
But I was able to talk to those with whom I could go
बट बात हो पाई उनसे जिनके साथ जा दे
At least one I still remember talking to
एटलीस्ट वन आई स्टिल रिमेंबर जिनसे बात
I couldn't give them to others whom I have
नहीं हो पाई दे आर अदर्स जिनको आई हैव
Given signals that I don't just want
गिवन सिग्नल्स कि आई डोंट नॉट ओनली वांट
to talk but i'm very eager to end whenever
टू टॉक बट आई एम वेरी इगर टू एंड व्हेनवर
they are ready i will be happy to maybe this
दे आर रेडी आई विल बी हैप्पी टू शायद ये
it happens with age yes beyond a point you
ऐज के साथ हो जाता है यस बियड अ पॉइंट यू
no look understand this also friends once in a while
नो देखिए ये भी समझिए दोस्तों में एक समय
after i might be theoretically possible
के बाद मैं हो सकता है थ्योरिटिकली पॉसिबल
But my understanding is that after a while the new
लेकिन मेरी समझ यह है कि एक समय के बाद नए
It becomes difficult to make friends. Ok
दोस्त बनाना मुश्किल हो जाता है। ठीक है
No? So the friends you grew up with
ना? तो जिन दोस्तों के साथ आप बड़े हुए
Assume those friends are in your mind
हैं उन दोस्तों की मान लीजिए आपके मन में
Or they have something very clear in their mind
या उनके मन में एकदम सख्त बिल्कुल क्लियर
It turns out you were wrong on one point.
रहा है कि आप एक पॉइंट पर गलत थे।
Its
इसके
Despite this, I have friendship with the same person
बावजूद उसी से व्यक्ति से के पास दोस्ती
Yet, there remains scope to do so.
करने की गुंजाइश फिर भी बनी रहती है।
Agreeing and Disagreeing on a Particular
एग्रीिंग और डिसएग्रीिंग ऑन अ पर्टिकुलर
The point is that you were wrong or I was wrong
पॉइंट कि इस जगह पर तू गलत था कि मैं गलत
Was. but new friends new friends once upon a time
था। लेकिन नए दोस्त नए दोस्त एक समय के
It is difficult to become later. more than a limit
बाद बनने मुश्किल है। एक लिमिट से ज्यादा
and that's why I always say new friends
और इसलिए मैं हमेशा कहता हूं नए दोस्तों
not to leave old friends for
के लिए पुराने दोस्तों को नहीं छोड़ना
Needed Now you can probably see this in your life
चाहिए। अब आप शायद इसको आपकी जिंदगी में
So he must have definitely come. We who are a
तो डेफिनेटली आया होगा। हम लोग जो एक
reached a particular level of fame, people
पर्टिकुलर लेवल ऑफ फेम पर पहुंचे, लोगों
reached the identities of, people started recognizing
की पहचानों तक पहुंचे, लोगों ने पहचानना
began. We have had major complaints
शुरू किया। हम लोगों से हुई बड़ी शिकायतों
This is one of the complaints given. now you are
में से एक शिकायत ये दी जाती है। अब तो तू
He has become a big man. why are you on our side
बड़ा आदमी हो गया है। आप क्यों हमारी तरफ
will you see? but i have realised that those are the two
देखेगा? बट आई हैव रियलाइज कि दो वे दोज़
which even today in terms of the fame and
जो कि आज भी इन टर्म्स ऑफ दी फेम एंड
Success and money and all is nothing or one
सक्सेस एंड मनी एंड ऑल कुछ नहीं है या एक
Living an average life. i make it a point
औसत जिंदगी जी रहे हैं। आई मेक इट अ पॉइंट
I am not saying that I will do it 100%
कि मैं ये तो नहीं कहता कि मैं 100% कर
I find that when I meet him, he has a
पाता हूं कि जब उनसे मिले तो उन्हें एक
Don't feel it even for a second. I give them this
सेकंड के लिए भी एहसास ना हो। मैं उनको ये
I provoke you sometimes I provoke you
प्रवोक करता हूं कई बार तो प्रवोक करता
I am literally thinking that he makes fun of me about this
हूं लिटरली कि वो मेरा मजाक उड़ाए इस बात
that yes friend you are right now, now you are
के कि हां यार तू तो अब सही है अब तू तो
Why is he talking to us after meeting Ranveer?
रणवीर से मिलके आ रहा है हमसे क्यों बात
will do that kind of thing ok because this
करेगा दैट काइंड ऑफ़ थिंग ठीक है बिकॉज़ दिस
is a right which I give only to the
इज अ राइट व्हिच आई गिव ओनली टू दी
friends this is a privilege this is a one
फ्रेंड्स दिस इज अ प्रिविलेज दिस इज अ एक
Dekhna is our Hindi word
देखना हमारे हिंदी में शब्द है
Privilege These privileges are my parents
विशेषाधिकार ये विशेषाधिकार मेरे पेरेंट्स
Neither do my family have it
के भी पास नहीं है मेरी फैमिली के भी पास
An unknown person doesn't have the courage
नहीं है अननोन व्यक्ति की तो हिम्मत नहीं
but friends have this
है लेकिन लेकिन दोस्तों के पास ये
privilege that they have over those things of mine
विशेषाधिकार है कि वे मेरी उन चीजों पर
Things that other people can make fun of
मजाक उड़ा सके जिन चीजों के लिए बाकी लोग
I praise you.
तारीफ करते हैं।
Brother, please make fun of me. How to quit
भाई मेरा मजाक उड़ा ना यार। कैसे छोड़
did you give it friend? sometimes now deliberately end as a
दिया यार तूने? कभी अब जानबूझ के एंड एज अ
communication person we know how to do it
कम्युनिकेशन पर्सन वी नो कि कैसे किया जा
Used to be. Is it okay? Now suppose this
रहा है। ठीक है ना? जैसे मान लीजिए अब ये
I said this Ranveer thing. So the
मैंने दिस आई सेड दिस रणवीर थिंग। तो जिस
At that time somebody must be doing this
समय कोई व्यक्ति कर रहा होगा उस समय जरा
sa tell me knowingly that this guy will catch this
सा बोल दे नोइंगली कि ये बंदा पकड़ेगा इस
To Cue. Will you catch this cue then?
क्यू को। इस क्यू को पकड़ेगा फिर तेरा
He will make fun of me. after that by doing that you
मजाक उड़ाएगा। उसके बाद हे कि करके आप
Will you feel shy? Come on friend, get up. Does anybody know
शर्माएंगे क्या? चल यार उठा। पता है कोई
also na sir a career about friends
भी ना सर दोस्तों के बारे में एक करियर
Doesn't talk from perspective. but this
पर्सपेक्टिव से बात नहीं करता। बट ये
I have observed it. again the reason for this show
मैंने ऑब्जर्व किया है। अगेन इस शो की वजह
I haven't learned much about life since
से ना मैंने जिंदगी के बारे में बहुत कुछ
Have you learnt. and top of the top people always have a
सीखा है। एंड टॉप ऑफ द टॉप पीपल हमेशा एक
There is always a small friend group. says
छोटा सा फ्रेंड ग्रुप तो रहता ही है। कहते
That Shahrukh Khan also has a core friend
हैं कि शाहरुख खान का भी एक कोर फ्रेंड
The group is still there. which they maintain
ग्रुप अभी भी है। जो वो मेंटेन करके रखते
Are. That is their rush in life. but no one
हैं। वो उनका रश है लाइफ में। बट नो वन
Nos who are his friends? no i know about
नोस कि उनके दोस्त कौन है? नो आई नो अबाउट
The Popular and Successful People They Crave
द पॉपुलर एंड सक्सेसफुल पीपल दे क्रेव दे
crave for this thing and those who for some
क्रेव फॉर दिस थिंग एंड दोज़ हु फॉर सम
the reason we've lost it
रीज़न हैव लॉस्ट इट
I I have full money because the price they have
आई आई हैव फुल एमथ बिकॉज़ द प्राइस दे हैव
Paid for this success is more than what
पेड फॉर दिस सक्सेस इज़ इज़ मोर देन व्हाट
is it worth the price loneliness one is
इज़ वर्थ वदी इज द प्राइस लोनलीनेस वन इज़
definitely loneliness and the second is that
डेफिनेटली लोनलीनेस एंड द सेकंड इज़ दैट
you run out of people who are your
आपके पास वह लोग खत्म हो जाते हैं जो आपकी
Looking you in the eye and telling you your mistakes
आंख में आंख डालकर आपको आपकी गलतियां बता
Could. It's not just loneliness. These
सके। ये सिर्फ लोनलीनेस नहीं है। ये
Well, loneliness has its place and you
लोनलीनेस तो खैर अपनी जगह पर है ही और यू
Rightly pointed it out. But if you
राइटली पॉइंटेड इट आउट। लेकिन अगर आपको
Someone, your childhood friend, is just like your eyes
कोई कोई आपका बचपन का दोस्त एकदम आंखों
I could not look into his eyes and say that Vijendra
में आंख डाल के ये ना कह सके कि विजेंद्र
You oppose something, it is correct
तुम अमुक चीज का विरोध करते हो सही बात
Is. But look at the boundary at this place
है। लेकिन देखो तुम इस जगह पर बाउंड्री को
You are crossing it. because someone else will say it
क्रॉस कर रहे हो। क्योंकि कोई और बोलेगा
So I'll assume it's a troll. But if any
तो मैं मान लूंगा ट्रॉल है। लेकिन अगर कोई
my friend will say then I will realize that
मेरा दोस्त बोलेगा देन आई विल रियलाइज कि
this person is just saying this to me
यह व्यक्ति सिर्फ मेरे लिए ऐसा बोल रहा
Is. On Friendship is the Treasure of Life
है। फ्रेंडशिप इज द ट्रेजर ऑफ लाइफ पर
Don't make so many friends that you
इतने ज्यादा दोस्त भी ना बनाओ कि आप
I will not be able to maintain friendship or you will be my friend
दोस्ती निभा ना पाओगे हम कि आप दोस्ती
I can't fulfill it Such a practical end
निभा ना पाओ। सच अ प्रैक्टिकल एंड
Important statement. Because suppose that
इंपॉर्टेंट स्टेटमेंट। क्योंकि मान लो कि
If you are career driven, you are going to be busy
अगर आप करियर ड्रिवन हो आप बिजी रहने वाले
yes. Family life in that busy schedule
हो। उस बिजी स्ेड्यूल में से फैमिली लाइफ
Putting it aside and spending time with friends
को साइड में करके दोस्त के साथ टाइम
It is difficult to spend. you have a limited
बिताना मुश्किल है। यू हैव अ लिमिटेड
Amount of friends you can keep? Yes. And
अमाउंट ऑफ़ फ्रेंड्स यू कैन कीप? यस। और
There is a big advantage in having more friends
ज्यादा दोस्तों के होने में फिर एक बड़ा
The problem is also that subconsciously you end up
संकट ये भी है कि सबकॉन्शियसली यू एंड अप
Substituting Comfortable Friends in the
सब्सीट्यूटिंग कंफर्टेबल फ्रेंड्स इन द
the place of friends who can make you
प्लेस ऑफ़ फ्रेंड्स हु कैन मेक यू
Uncomfortable. Which is again awkwardness.
अनकंफर्टेबल। व्हिच इज़ अगेन अशुडनेस।
That means there should be depth in friendship too.
मतलब वही ना दोस्ती में भी डेप्थ चाहिए।
That is what friendship is for. yes butt
दैट इज व्हाट फ्रेंडशिप इज फॉर। हां बट
Be careful in friendship like fame
देन दोस्ती में ध्यान रखिएगा जैसे फेम
As if money is not a criteria. same way
जैसे पैसा क्राइटेरिया नहीं है। वैसे ही
If I'm a little older than you
अगर मैं आपसे थोड़ी सी उम्र में बड़ा हूं
And if I can give advice then I am telling you. By the way
और सलाह दे सकता हूं तो कह रहा हूं। वैसे
only
ही
Don't make intellectual equality a condition.
इंटेलेक्चुअल बराबरी को भी शर्त मत बनाइए।
What happens many times is that you find yourself
हम कई बार क्या होता है कि आप अपने आपको
Because you have experience.
क्योंकि आपने आपके पास एक्सपीरियंस है।
You have a particular track of life
आपके पास जिंदगी का एक पर्टिकुलर ट्रैक
So you think that now you can't
रहा इसलिए आप सोचते हैं कि अब आप
Let's go to the abstract level. Now you
एब्स्ट्रैक्ट लेवल पर जाते हैं। अब आपको
The principles make sense. Philosophy to you
सिद्धांत समझ में आते हैं। आपको फिलॉसफी
I understand it. You understand spirituality
समझ में आती है। आपको स्पिरिचुअलिटी समझ
It comes in. That is why your friend who is
में आती है। इस कारण आपका वह दोस्त जो इस
Has not gone through the process. he is not
प्रोसेस से नहीं गुजरा है। ही इज नॉट
Uniform. Don't conclude that. This is from late 20s
वर्दी। डोंट कंक्लूड दैट। ये लेट 20ज की
Many people make mistakes. till late 20
बहुतों की मिस्टेक होती है। लेट 20 तक तो
Little does one know that a good career
थोड़ा पता चल जाता है कि अच्छा करियर में
Do this. I have grown out. Him You Never
ये कर। आई हैव आउट ग्रोन। हिम यू नेवर
Outgrow your friends.
आउटग्रो योर फ्रेंड्स।
[Laughter]
[हंसी]
Where did you start from? How far have you reached? I
कहां से शुरुआत किया? कहां तक पहुंचे? आई
mean that's the fun of being Ranveer and you are
मीन दैट्स द फन ऑफ़ बीइंग रणवीर एंड यू आर
Able to extract things which I have
एबल टू एक्सट्रैक्ट थिंग्स व्हिच आई हैव
Not said on camera to almost anybody. I
नॉट सेड ऑन कैमरा टू ऑलमोस्ट एनीबडी। आई
I am glad sir. I hope I get to meet you
एम ग्लैड सर। आई होप आई गेट टू मीट यू
Again in life. That's all I say. Had fun
अगेन इन लाइफ। दैट्स ऑल आई से। मजा आ गया
With you. Thank you. Thank you very much. Vary
आपके साथ। थैंक यू। थैंक यू वैरी मच। वैरी
Memorable afternoon sir. I genuinely hope that
मेमरेबल आफ्टरनून सर। आई जेनुइनली होप कि
Audience Haze
ऑडियंस हैज़
Rhinoceros
गेंड
Value. Hopefully for the next 30 years.
वैल्यू। होपफुली अगले 30 सालों के लिए।
Thank you. Thank you Ranveer. thank you for
थैंक यू। थैंक यू रणवीर। थैंक यू फॉर
Being with us Vijay sir. sorry to call you vijay
बीइंग वि अस विजय सर। सॉरी टू कॉल यू विजय
Sir. Just about everyone calls you Vijay Sir. there
सर। बस कोई भी आपको विजय सर कहता है। देयर
is a friend. Ok. just want to know
इज अ फ्रेंड। ओके। जस्ट वांट टू कन्व
Great. That's all I would like to say. and I
ग्रेट। बस उतना ही कहना चाहूंगा। एंड आई
Genuinely hope life makes us meet again.
जेन्युइनली होप लाइफ मेक्स अस मीट अगेन।
many more conversations i would love to have with
मेनी मोर कन्वर्सेशन आई वुड लव टू हैव विथ
You over the years. Thank you so much. Thank you.
यू ओवर दी इयर्स। थैंक यू सो मच। थैंक यू।
Thank you so much. So friends, tell me how are you
थैंक यू सो मच। तो दोस्तों, बताइए कैसा
Did you like today's episode? As many as our country
लगा आज का एपिसोड? जितने भी हमारे देश के
There are great UPSC coaches and UPSC
महान यूपीएससी कोचेस हैं और यूपीएससी
are celebrities of the coaching circuit, their
कोचिंग सर्किट के सेलिब्रिटीज हैं, उनके
We always want to have such deep conversations with each other
साथ ना हमेशा ऐसी ही डीप कन्वर्सेशंस करने
I get a chance. Give me feedback on this
का एक चांस मिल जाता है। फीडबैक दीजिए ये
Let me know how you liked the episode and if you found it valuable.
एपिसोड कैसा लगा बताइए और अगर आपको वैल्यू
got it from this episode then definitely
मिला इस एपिसोड में से तो फिर डेफिनेटली
Please recommend TRS. to other people like
टीआरएस रेकमेंड कीजिए। दूसरे लोगों को ऐसे
The podcasts will keep coming. podcasts where
ही पॉडकास्ट आते रहेंगे। ऐसे पडकास्ट जहां
There were talks about practical things
प्रैक्टिकल चीजों के बारे में बातें होती
that you can adopt in your life
है जिन्हें आप अपने लाइफ में अपना सकते
yes. These are podcasts which are worth it
हो। यह होते हैं पडकास्ट व्हिच आर वर्थ
Spending your time on. a if I had a
स्पेंडिंग योर टाइम ऑन। अ अगर मैंने एक
released a piece where I feel
ऐसा पीस रिलीज किया जहां मुझे लगता है कि
Yes my audience will watch this piece two-three times
हां मेरी ऑडियंस इस पीस को दो-तीन बार
It will consume. then my heart is satisfied
कंज्यूम करेगी। फिर मेरे दिल को संतुष्टि
It is available. So thank you for listening in. End
मिलती है। तो थैंक यू फॉर लिसनिंग इन। एंड
I hope this episode helps you a lot. Just like that
आई होप दिस एपिसोड हेल्प यू अ लॉट। ऐसे ही
Many episodes will be released in the coming days
बहुत सारे एपिसोड रिलीज होंगे आने वाले
In a few weeks. Thank you.
कुछ हफ्तों में। थैंक यू।
yes
हो
[music]
[संगीत]